<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Ryan Hayden</title>
    <link href="https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog" />
    <link type="application/atom+xml" rel="self" href="https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/feed.atom" />
    <updated>2022-12-09T22:41:27+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/feed.atom</id>
    <author>
        <name>Ryan Hayden</name>
    </author>
                <entry>
    <id>https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/2022-12-09-leaving-company</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/2022-12-09-leaving-company" />
    <title>Leaving the Company I Cofounded</title>
    <published>2022-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2022-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Ryan Hayden</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">The last few months have been some of the craziest months of my life:


To start, my son Noah has been going through some yet-undefined health crisis that has required lots of two hour one-way trips to specialists.    We still haven&#039;t figured out what is......</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>The last few months have been some of the craziest months of my life:</p>

<ul>
<li>To start, my son Noah has been going through some yet-undefined health crisis that has required lots of two hour one-way trips to specialists.    We still haven't figured out what is causing his issues.</li>
<li>We had a fifth child.  We now have a 13 year old, a 12 year old, a 9 year old, a two year old and a 3 month old.  So on top of doing the teenager thing, we have two babies in the house again.  Even without Noah's issues this would be incredibly stressful.</li>
<li>Our church is showing signs of growth, including lots of visitors and purchasing adjacent property.  I feel like this is a critical juncture in the life of our church and that our church needs leadership right now.</li>
</ul>

<p>In the middle of all of that, a couple of things happened:</p>

<ol>
<li>I realized I wasn't being a very good business partner.  My children's health issues and my commitment to my church was severely limiting my usefulness to my company.</li>
<li>I realized I wasn't being a very good pastor.  I was faithfully preaching, but had little left in the tank to shepherd our church.</li>
<li>I realized that, if I could do anything, I wouldn't be doing software for hire.  I love software, but I am no business guy, and I wanted to give my time to church work.</li>
</ol>

<p><img src="/assets/img/bo2.jpeg" alt="" /></p>

<p>So, I'm in the process of exiting the company I started and returning to some kind of "full time ministry."  I'm still going to have to do some work on the side (I have five kids after all), but I want my main thing (after my family) to be Bible Baptist Church.  For now, that is enough.</p>

<p>I want to say to all of the people who I got to work with at Build Online - thank you from the bottom of my heart.  I never in my wildest dreams imagined I would get to start a company and work with such awesome people building such cool things.   Waking up every day to solve problems with you was incredibly fulfilling.  Flying around the country to do discovery meetings gave me some incredible memories I'll never forget.  Seeing you grow has been amazing.  You may have started as coworkers, but you became dear friends, and I'm grateful for the time we got to spend together.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/bo3.jpeg" alt="" /></p>

<p>To my business partners, I want to say a special thank you.  We went on quite a journey together and I respect you as much as any two people I know.  I'm not a gambling man, but I'd bet on your success any day.  Thank you for your friendship and kindness, especially in the last few difficult months when my time has been so dominated by what's been going on with my family.</p>

<p>To our clients I want to say you are in great hands.  The developers at Build Online are some of the smartest people I've ever met.  Luke Miller is a modern Joseph, and everything he touches gets better because he is there.  Further, both the owners and the team at Build Online are people of integrity who I trust to do the right thing even if it hurts them.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/bo4.jpeg" alt="" /></p>

<p>I remember being a poor newly-graduated school teacher who used to go to Barnes and Nobles and read books on web development that I couldn't afford.  I remember driving by the local web development shop on a commute and dreaming about working at a place like that.  I remember looking at some of the web apps that are out there and dreaming of what it must be like to be on there team.  Somehow, with Build Online, I got to live out all of those fantasies and more.  It truly was a fulfillment of Matthew 6:33 for me:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>But seek ye first the kingdom of God, and his righteousness; and all these things shall be added unto you.</p>
  
  <blockquote>
    <p>Matthew 6:33</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>Like a young sailor returning from his first voyage, maybe I had to see the great big world to really appreciate my own little hamlet and to fully take up my place in it.  The biggest thing I think I've learned from this is that I am a pastor all the way down and to be a pastor is no small thing.</p>

<p>I think I'll always program (indeed, I'm working on a project right now), but whatever I do will be primarily for my church and churches like it, because that is where my heart is.</p>

<p>I'm hoping to return to making more devotional videos, possibly doing some podcasting, and I'm even considering some advanced theological education, but for the next few months I think I'm going to take it easy, get back in shape and reconnect with my family and church family.</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/2020-12-08-preaching-rule-2</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/2020-12-08-preaching-rule-2" />
    <title>Rules for preaching: Don&#039;t Come Up With A Message</title>
    <published>2022-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2022-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Ryan Hayden</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">In this series of posts, I&#039;m writing out my personal rules for preaching.  These are the things I would want to teach a young preacher in training coming up under my ministry.

In the first rule, I talked about how preaching isn&#039;t about the preacher.  I......</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>In this series of posts, I'm writing out my personal rules for preaching.  These are the things I would want to teach a young preacher in training coming up under my ministry.</p>

<p>In the first rule, I talked about how preaching isn't about the preacher.  I want to carry that thought further with this second rule:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It's not your job to "come up with a message"</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Sometimes I'll hear preachers use this language.  I know they mean well.  But <strong>words mean things</strong> and there is a lot of danger in this seemingly benign phrase.  In dealing with that danger we can get to the heart of what separates good preaching from bad preaching.</p>

<h2>The limits of creativity</h2>

<p>When you preach a message, it should not primarily be an act of your creativity.  You might imagine yourself to be like an artist staring at a blank canvas.  You might imagine yourself like a novelist staring at a blank page.  But those imaginations are wrong and dangerous.</p>

<p><strong>Your job is not to create a message.  Your job is to deliver a message that has already been given.</strong>  Making the act of preaching primarily about your creativity moves the authority from God and His word to you and your imagination.</p>

<p>Again, going back to the first rule: it's not about you.  You are not the hero of this story.  The people you are preaching to are not the hero of this story.  God is the hero of this story.  He's also the author and the provider and He has already given people what they need through His word.  You just have to deliver it.</p>

<p>When we send kids to school, the teacher should not be making it up as she goes along.  The teacher has a curriculum that she teaches, she has goals and objectives she is supposed to be working towards.  She should not go into the classroom every day and think "what do I teach today?"  That decision is above her pay grade.  Her job is to get the students before her to understand the curriculum and learn the lessons someone else decided.</p>

<p>If you are a preacher, it's not your job to come up with a lesson.  You have a curriculum - it's the "whole council of God."  You have clear goals and objectives.  You don't get to make it up as you go along - that decision is above your pay grade. God gets to decide what people need - not you.  You are just there to teach the lessons and curriculum God created for you.</p>

<p>We've all heard horrible sermons before where the preacher made applications that were totally cringeworthy.  There is an easy way to avoid that - stick to the text.</p>

<h2>Discover, don't create</h2>

<p>It's not your job to "come up with a message", your job is to discover the message that is already there.  Every text has a message.  Every text has a meaning.  You just need to figure out what that text means and how it applies to today and then teach that authoritatively to the people you are preaching to.</p>

<p>When I approach a text, I'm not thinking "how do I come up with a message?" - <strong>the message is is already there</strong>.  I just need to figure out what it is and then help people understand it and obey it.</p>

<p>The core of writing a sermon isn't creating, it's understanding and discovery.  Before I ever apply my creativity, I need to do the work to understand THE message God intended by the text.  Without doing this work, my message will have no authority and no power.  Without doing this work, I'm more likely to hurt people than to help people.</p>

<p>Imagine a chef applying their unbelievable cooking skills to prepare a meal out of <em>plastic.</em>  It might smell amazing.  It might be presented beautifully.  It might even taste good.  But it's still plastic and it will still hurt you.  You'd be better served going to someone who can't cook at all who just gives you raw vegetables.  It might not taste as good - but it won't kill you and it will sustain you.</p>

<p>If you apply creativity too early, it's like trying to serve a meal without any actual food. Maybe you can impress people, but that meal isn't going to keep anyone alive and it will probably kill them.</p>

<h2>When creativity comes into play</h2>

<p>It is only after you have done the work of discovering what a text means that you apply creativity.  You aren't using creativity to come up with a message, you are using creativity to help people understand the message.</p>

<p>Going back to the teacher analogy.  We don't want our teachers getting creative with the curriculum (see LibsofTiktok on twitter for how that works out) but great teachers use all kinds of creative ways to keep our kids engaged so they can learn the pre-approved curriculum.  They think up games.  They come up with unique assignments.  They decorate their classrooms.  They write little songs. 
Teachers have to be creative, just creative within the limits their curriculum.</p>

<p>In preaching, we absolutely need to be creative, we just don't apply our creativity to <em>coming up with a message</em> we apply our creativity only after we have understood the message God has given us.  There is all kinds of room for creativity in delivery and explanation, but only applied to understanding the message God gave us.</p>

<h2>God's message is better than yours</h2>

<p>I remember a "sermon" I once heard.  The preacher stood up before the people with a Winnie the Pooh puzzle and the main thrust of the message was something like "You fit in God's puzzle."</p>

<p>A Winnie the Pooh puzzle!? Why?  Of all of the vast and wonderful content in the Bible, this preacher thought we needed a direct word from Winnie the Pooh!</p>

<p>I remember this episode because it is such an extreme example of what many preachers do all the time: they sidestep God's wonderful word to share their own obviously inferior message.  I sat under a preacher once who was a good man, but every sermon I remember him preaching was some bizarre departure from the text.  The applications of those sermons were almost always whatever thing he was into at the moment.</p>

<p>God has given us a message.  We have "the whole council of God."  It's so vast that it would take us  many lifetimes for us to preach it all.   Our job as preachers is, first and foremost, to figure out what that pre-existing message is and to deliver it to people.  Even if all we did was read the Bible to people, that would be far more valuable than us coming up with something on our own.</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/2022-11-22-rule-one-its-not-about-you</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/2022-11-22-rule-one-its-not-about-you" />
    <title>Rules for preaching: It&#039;s not about you</title>
    <published>2022-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2022-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Ryan Hayden</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">I plan on writing a series of posts on my ten rules for preaching.

These are just my rules.   They are some things I&#039;ve learned about preaching that I try to apply to my own ministry.  If I were to mentor someone on preaching, these are the things I&#039;d......</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>I plan on writing a series of posts on my ten rules for preaching.</p>

<p>These are just <em>my</em> rules.   They are some things I've learned about preaching that I try to apply to my own ministry.  If I were to mentor someone on preaching, these are the things I'd want them to learn.</p>

<p>Let's get this thing started with...</p>

<h1>Rule 1: It's not about you</h1>

<p>There are few things that feed the ego more than standing in front of a large room full of people who <em>seem</em> to be listening to you with rapt attention and authoritatively preaching to them.  If you aren't careful to do otherwise, you can begin to make the whole calling and the whole act of preaching about <em>you</em> - and when you do, you will miss the entire point.</p>

<h2>You are not the point.</h2>

<p>The point is Christ.  The point is the <em>unfolding drama of redemption.</em>  The point is the glory of God.  The point is the rescue of souls.  The point is the building up of believers into a glorious church.</p>

<p>You, as the preacher, don't play the central role in that - Christ does.  The Holy Spirit does.  The Bible does.  You are just the herald, reading with enthusiasm the good news someone else wrote up for you.</p>

<p>To borrow my favorite illustration from John MacArthur: You are not the chef. You are certainly not the meal. <strong>You are the waiter.</strong>  No one cares about the waiter.  The waiter does his job and then the waiter disappears.  You want the waiter to faithfully serve you your food and then you want the check.  You didn't come to the restaurant excited about the waiter - you came excited about the meal.</p>

<p><strong>As soon as it becomes about you then you've lost the plot.</strong>  There are far more glorious things on the table, and you are a distraction.  There is a word that is alive and can change people, and you are in the way.  Make much of Christ.  Make much of God's word.  Make yourself forgettable.</p>

<h2>You are not that interesting.</h2>

<p>Or to put it more bluntly: nobody cares about you.</p>

<p>I tell my children this all the time.  They seem to think that everyone is thinking about them all the time.  They interpret every sour look as an attack and every anonymous chuckle as someone making fun of them.  But that person looks sour because they ate some bad pizza, and that couple is chuckling because their two year old just stuck a booger on tip of his nose.</p>

<p>It is a rule of human nature that no one thinks about you.  They think about themselves.  They think about what they want, what they are eating for lunch after the service, how they are going to pay their bills this month, how they are going to get their estranged son back in the fold.  They are thinking about their problems.</p>

<p>So if you get behind a pulpit and talk about yourself, not only are you going to be bringing a message with absolutely zero power to help anyone, but your people will pick up on what's going on, check out, and start thinking about their grocery list, counting down the minutes until its all over.</p>

<p>Charles Spurgeon said the golden key to keeping people's attention is to say something worth listening to.  Spoiler alert: the details of your life, your quirky views about weird subjects, and how you feel about things aren't worth listening to.</p>

<h2>You are not the hero.</h2>

<p>Christ is the hero.  So talk about Christ.  Make much of Him.  Talk a lot about his redemption.  Bring every story back to it's place in the gospel.</p>

<p>God is the hero.  God loves us.  God has given us wonderful instructions for life.  God has given us mercy.  God has given us grace.  God will give us the help we need to make it through.</p>

<p>Seriously, what kind of demented egomaniac opens the words of life that are sweeter than honeycomb and more valuable than fine gold and then talks about <em>himself</em> for thirty minutes?  Imagine going to the colosseum in Rome and trying to talk to passersby about the layout of your bedroom.  Imagine hiking up to the top of Mt. Denali and then standing at the top and taking a picture of your outfit.  If you truly understood where you were you would shut up and <em>wonder.</em>  Nothing cheapens the glory or makes you look smaller than your desperate attempt to say <em>look at me</em> when God is in the room.</p>

<p>If you must talk about yourself never, ever, ever make yourself the hero of the story.  Don't get me wrong, it's far better to not talk about yourself at all - but if you must, then you must remember that you are not the hero - you are the bumbling nitwit God rescued.  Christ is the hero.  Bear testimony of that fact or get off the stage.</p>

<h2>You should aim to disappear.</h2>

<p>One of my favorite stories is when an American went to London on a Sunday and got to hear two of the greatest preachers ever on the same day.  During the morning service he went to hear the great Joseph Parker and he came away incredibly impressed by the <em>preacher</em>.  For the evening service he went to hear Charles Spurgeon and he came away incredibly impressed by the <em>Savior</em>.</p>

<p>I want the people who hear me to be impressed by Jesus, not by me.  I want them to wander at God's mercy and grace and to get caught up in beautiful wisdom of God.  If I'm doing my job right, they will forget I'm even there.</p>

<p>When I preach the word, I'm not the point, I'm not the hero, I'm not that interesting, I'm certainly not the solution to people's problems - at my best I'm a giant arrow pointing people to Christ - because He is the solution, the hero and the one who deserves all of the glory.</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/What-I-have-been-up-to</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/What-I-have-been-up-to" />
    <title>What I&#039;ve Been Up To</title>
    <published>2022-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2022-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Ryan Hayden</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">A month ago, I spent a few days in a children&#039;s hospital with my son.  I had a lot of time to think, and these or some of the things I thought:



Its been three years since I worked on a project with complete autonomy.  I&#039;ve spent those years learning a......</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>A month ago, I spent a few days in a children's hospital with my son.  I had a lot of time to think, and these or some of the things I thought:</p>

<h2>1. I really want to code again.</h2>

<p>Its been three years since I worked on a project with complete autonomy.  I've spent those years learning a ton about making software while managing a team of developers.  But I really miss being able to just open a text editor and create something <strong>useful.</strong></p>

<p>I want to see what's possible for one guy to do using modern tooling, good product design and as many helps as possible.</p>

<h2>2. I really want to make something that somehow enhances church life.</h2>

<p>I'm not interested in church marketing.  I'm not interested in the flashy and the new.  I want to make something that takes the very basics of what a church is (worship, prayer, Bible teaching, fellowship) and helps people do it better.  Something that would benefit a large church in a suburb as well as a church of thirty that's two hours from anywhere.</p>

<h2>3. I really despise sharing prayer requests on social media.</h2>

<p>If you've ever had a kid going through a major health crisis, then maybe you can understand this.  A sick kid is an attention magnet.  A sick kid garners all kinds of sympathy.  That's not always what you want when you are dealing with problems.  I really want to update the people I know <em>in real life</em> about my son's condition, but facebook magnifies that in a way that (I think) is unhealthy.</p>

<p>While I'm at it, <strong>I despise Facebook</strong>. It's all ads for things I don't want.  Political posts from people who don't really know anything about politics or show off pictures of people's vacation or new home.</p>

<p>Further, I currently have 1,773 facebook "friends."  Many of them are old class mates, or distant family members, or people I went to church with at some point, but just as many of them are acquaintances or even strangers.  But I can't possibly care about 1,773 people.</p>

<h2>4. I really miss the churchtools.co prayer app.</h2>

<p>Years ago I made a simple app for prayer requests.  Basically, it was just a database for managing a church's prayer request list that outputted a PDF you could print out as a bulletin for a prayer meeting.  That little app saved me (or a volunteer or secretary) at least 30 minutes every week.  I know a lot of other churches liked it too.  Of all the things I've made for churches, that was probably the most unique and the one thing I wish never died.  I really wish I had developed that idea.</p>

<h2>I think you can see where all this is going...</h2>

<p>I decided it was time to make an app again.</p>

<p>So, for the last month, I've been getting up at 5:00a.m. six days a week so I could get a few hours in on the church prayer app before work.  I didn't want to tell anyone about it, because I've announced a few things that never got built.  (Still hoping to get Mission Hosts off the ground - that one's a bit more technically challenging than this one is.)</p>

<p>But now I feel like I've gotten enough done that the finish line is in sight and I'm ready to start talking about it.</p>

<h2>So what is the church prayer app?</h2>

<p>The church prayer app is a very basic social network, where the only other people are people in your local church and the only thing you can share are prayer requests and encouraging comments/questions about prayer requests.</p>

<ul>
<li>It's not a CRM.</li>
<li>It's not a marketing tool.</li>
<li>It's not flashy and cutting edge.</li>
</ul>

<p>It's just me taking the church prayer list, something that has probably existed (and been a slight hassle to keep up with) since the book of Acts and using the power of software to teach it some new tricks.  New tricks like:</p>

<ul>
<li>Auto-archiving prayer requests.</li>
<li>Sending SMS notifications for urgent requests.</li>
<li>Comments and a likes system.</li>
<li>iOS and Android apps.</li>
<li>Content moderation so it doesn't grow out of control.</li>
<li>PDF generation for bulletin inserts/prayer meeting handouts.</li>
<li>A weekly prayer request email for those who don't want to be part of the app.</li>
<li>Exporting to InDesign/Affinity Publisher (and some starter templates) for larger churches.</li>
</ul>

<h2>When will it be ready?</h2>

<p>I'm aiming to have it ready for my church to start using by the end of next week, and after testing it thoroughly, turning it on for the masses at the end of November.</p>

<h2>What will you call it?</h2>

<p>I'm planning on just calling it "The Church Prayer App."  (I own thechurchprayerapp.com)</p>

<h2>How much will it cost?</h2>

<p>I'm planning on the basic functionality being free.  If you just want to use it as a church prayer network - that won't cost anything.</p>

<p>But I will be adding premium features that will come as part of an affordable premium plan (less than $10 per church per month.)  Those features will definitely include customization, printing handouts, sending SMS messages, and some other features that will help the church staff manage the list.</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/noah-update-10-6</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/noah-update-10-6" />
    <title>Noah Update 10-6-22</title>
    <published>2022-10-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2022-10-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Ryan Hayden</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">We are on the road heading home from Noah&#039;s Biopsy and lots of people are asking for an update and results so here you go.

We were hoping that the biopsy would confirm that Noah had something called TINU Syndrome, which is a rare and fairly treatable......</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>We are on the road heading home from Noah's Biopsy and lots of people are asking for an update and results so here you go.</p>

<p>We were hoping that the biopsy would confirm that Noah had something called TINU Syndrome, which is a rare and fairly treatable condition Noah's symptoms seemed to point to.  Unfortunately, the biopsy did not confirm that diagnosis.  Here is what we learned:</p>

<h2>The Good News</h2>

<p>The good news is that Noah has no active inflammation in his kidneys.  (This is what they were looking for to confirm TINU.)  Whatever is causing his issues, isn't currently active in his kidneys.</p>

<h2>The Bad News</h2>

<p>The bad news is that 50% of the tissue they sampled was scarred and damaged.  Whatever Noah was going through did a number on his kidneys.</p>

<h2>The Silver Lining</h2>

<p>Based on the labs and the observation of the hospital, his kidneys seem to be functioning fairly well.  They believe his young body has adjusted and the damage is not extensive enough for him to need a kidney transplant or dialysis.</p>

<h2>More Questions</h2>

<p>I think the worst thing for us is we still don't know what is causing all of Noah's issues.  The doctors have ordered more tests and hinted at something even rarer than TINU.  For now, he's fine, and they are going to treat his symptoms and keep a watch on his kidneys.</p>

<p>They had him see a specialist pediatric dermatologist while in the hospital.  She has adjusted his medication and they are going to start seeing him there.  We are super happy with the doctors and nurses at Children's in St. Louis, but really wish it wasn't over two hours away.  We are going to be making a lot of trips there.</p>

<p>What's the real estate market look like for AirBnB's in St. Louis?</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/update-on-noah-10-4</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/update-on-noah-10-4" />
    <title>An Update on Noah - 10-04-22</title>
    <published>2022-10-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2022-10-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Ryan Hayden</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">Noah had a biopsy on his kidney today at St. Louis Children&#039;s Hospital.  We stayed in St. Louis overnight and reported to the hospital this morning at 8:30am.



When he got into his pre-op room, they put him in the hospital pajamas.  Apparently, they......</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>Noah had a biopsy on his kidney today at St. Louis Children's Hospital.  We stayed in St. Louis overnight and reported to the hospital this morning at 8:30am.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/hosptial_gown.jpeg" alt="" /></p>

<p>When he got into his pre-op room, they put him in the hospital pajamas.  Apparently, they only make them in like two sizes: huge and tiny.  He's wearing the tiny ones.</p>

<p>There were some complications with the biopsy and he was bleeding internally for a little more than an hour.  But after a lot of hand-wringing, it stopped on its own and his blood pressure almost immediately went back to normal without the need for a transfusion or even for medicine.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/hospital_room.jpeg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Currently, we are in a room on the 11th floor with a fantastic view over Forrest Park.  Noah has to lay flat for several more hours, but he's enjoying watching movies and playing video games.  He's telling me now how he doesn't feel out of it.</p>

<p>The doctors and nurses here have been great.  We should know preliminary results from the biopsy by the morning.</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/moving-on-from-obsidian-publish</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/moving-on-from-obsidian-publish" />
    <title>Moving On From Obsidian Publish</title>
    <published>2022-10-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2022-10-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Ryan Hayden</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">I spent some time this weekend setting up a proper blog, and moving my content from Obsidian Publish over to here.  I want to explain why and how I did it, and talk about why I love the idea of Obsidian Publish but not the execution.



The reason I paid......</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>I spent some time this weekend setting up a proper blog, and moving my content from Obsidian Publish over to here.  I want to explain why and how I did it, and talk about why I love the idea of Obsidian Publish but not the execution.</p>

<h2>Why I signed up for Obsidian Publish</h2>

<p>The reason I paid $20 per month to setup Obsidian Publish in the first place is because I loved the idea of being able to blog my notes directly from my note writing software, without having to do any configuration.</p>

<p>Obsidian Publish is indeed great for that.  You write.  You click the publish button.  It magically shows up on your site.  It could not get easier and does exactly what its supposed to.</p>

<h2>Why I moved on</h2>

<p>As great as Obsidian Publish is, and as much as I loved the ease of publishing, there were some problems I ran into that, for me, didn't justify the subscription.</p>

<h3>First, Obsidian Publish is too expensive</h3>

<p>At $20 per month, I just couldn't justify that expense for my hobby blog.  Maybe if it did everything I wanted it to, I'd change my mind, but almost immediately I had buyer's remorse.</p>

<h3>Second, Obsidian Publish isn't really made for blogging.</h3>

<p>It's made for publishing your notes.  It's very, very good at publishing your notes.  But notes are not a blog. Publish was lacking on these fronts:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Appearance:</strong> I really disliked the way Obsidian Publish made my blog look.  I love the three pane look for my notes, but not for my blog.  I wouldn't want to read a blog that looked like that, and I doubt my readers did either.</li>
<li><strong>Comments:</strong> I couldn't setup comments.  That was a promised feature of Obsidian Publish that hasn't come to be yet.  Having comments is half the fun of having a blog.</li>
<li><strong>Sharing:</strong> I didn't like the way Obsidian Publish links looked when shared on Social Media.  Despite photos being at the top of my posts, they never showed a preview photo.  People didn't know what to do with the link.</li>
<li><strong>Navigation:</strong> I didn't like the way Obsidian Publish's folder structure worked for a blog.  The sidebar with Areas > Blog and Resources > Readwise didn't make sense to people.</li>
</ul>

<p>Yes, I could make publish better by customizing it, but I came to the realization that I was asking a hammer to be a screw driver and would never be happy with how it looked as long as I was trying to do something it wasn't intended for.</p>

<h2>What I'm doing now</h2>

<p>I've switched this blog over to a static site generator called <a href="https://jigsaw.tighten.com">Jigsaw</a>.  Jigsaw is made using Laravel, Vue and Tailwind - three technologies I work in every day, so customizing it will be second nature for me.  I'm using the standard blog template, which I find to be very good, and I plan to slowly customize it and to add some tools for sermons.</p>

<p>I'm writing some shell scripts on my computer that take a file from Obsidian, edit it to match what Jigsaw expects, and moves it into the folder.  So publishing will be fairly easy.</p>

<p>And I'm hosting the blog on <a href="https://pages.github.com">github pages</a> - so its basically free.</p>

<h2>Let me know what you think</h2>

<p>Let me know what you think in the comments below.  What would you change?  What would you add?  I'm curious.</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/the-power-of-changing-your-self-identity</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/the-power-of-changing-your-self-identity" />
    <title>The Power of Changing Your Self-Identity</title>
    <published>2022-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2022-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Ryan Hayden</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">In this post, I&#039;m going to make a point about our Christian walk that applies to everybody.  I think it&#039;s a powerful point.  Unfortunately, I have to talk about diets and health food to get there.  So if you can wade through a few paragraphs, I promise......</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>In this post, I'm going to make a point about our Christian walk that applies to everybody.  I think it's a powerful point.  Unfortunately, I have to talk about diets and health food to get there.  So if you can wade through a few paragraphs, I promise it will be worth it.  I promise I'm not trying to get you to change your diet and this isn't a health-food flex.</p>

<p>Here we go...</p>

<p>\<Begin Boring Health Talk\></p>

<p>Recently, because of all my son Noah is going through, we decided to put him on a gluten free diet.  To be clear, this likely isn't doing anything.  No doctor prescribed this.  It was just something several friends with auto-immune issues said may help and so we decided to try it.  It seems to be helping Noah, even if it's just a placebo effect.</p>

<p>Because I didn't want Noah doing it alone, I decided that I would do it to. 
 <strong>And just like that, in an instant, I became "gluten-free."</strong></p>

<p>Thousands of things I've eaten all my life were immediately off-limits: pizza, everything that comes out of a bakery, anything that comes in a Little Debby's box, fried chicken...the list goes on and on.  Trips to restaurants just got a whole lot more complicated.  Just about all fast food is off the table.</p>

<p>And it's not been bad.  Gluten free pizza is kind of good.  I've come to really enjoy my gluten free whole grain toast in the morning.  Plenty of really good food doesn't have flour in it.  (And to evidence this, I've only lost negative two pounds in the last two weeks.)</p>

<p>I've always made fun of gluten free.  My mother has to eat gluten free for a health condition and my brother's and I teased her about it all the time and refused to eat anything that was gluten free.  She was always saying "try this gluten free cake" and we wouldn't touch it.  It seemed to us akin to the eating kale chips, drinking almond milk, or being a vegetarian.  At best a legitimate allergy or food sensitivity, but just as often a weird hippy virtue signal.</p>

<p>But that was then and now is now.</p>

<p>Here is my point:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>When you change your self-identity, your behaviors and interests follow suit.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>For two weeks, I haven't even been tempted to eat something with gluten in it.  Immediately, after I made that decision, after I became "gluten-free" a whole lot of things I used to enjoy just weren't for me.  In an instant I changed a part of my identify to be "someone who doesn't eat gluten" and in an instant, my behavior's and desires changed.</p>

<p>It hasn't been hard.  I don't lay awake at night pining for New York Style pizza or French baguettes.  I drive down the road and places I used to love have no appeal now.  <strong>Because that isn't who I am anymore.</strong>  (At least for now.)</p>

<p>\&lt;\/End Boring Health Talk&#62;</p>

<p>Now, I don't want to to talk about diet here.  I want to talk about being a Christian and living the Christian life.  I believe there is a powerful analogy here to how we live, and it's in the Bible.</p>

<p>When we change our self-identity, our behavior and interests follows suit.  Then, as we behave in a way that matches our new self-identity, it reinforces our new identity and makes it even easier to stay on that path.  This is made really clear in <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Atomic-Habits-Proven-Build-Break/dp/0735211299">James Clear's book Atomic Habits</a>.  (The image below is from James Clear)</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/habit-layers.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>At some point in my life, I convinced myself I was a writer.  Then, because I was a writer, I wrote.  After I wrote awhile, and people seemed to respond well to it, it reinforced that identity.  Now there is lots of evidence (about 5,000 words a week worth) that I am, in fact, a writer.  But it started by changing the way I view myself.</p>

<p>God wants us as Christians to be a <em>holy people</em> and set apart to Him (1 Peter 2:9).   The Bible teaches that when we trust Christ we are born again and old things are passed away and all things become new. (2 Corinthians 5:17) We instantly go from being part of the rot of the world to being the salt that preserves it.  We go from being the darkness to being the light. (Matthew 5:13-20)</p>

<p>Christians, in other words, get a massive identity change and our behavior and desires should follow that new identity.  There should be lots of things you used to enjoy or used to desire where you simply say "that's not for me anymore, I'm a Christian now."</p>

<ul>
<li>Music that elevates sex and drunkenness and denigrates women - that's not for me anymore, I'm a Christian.</li>
<li>TV, movies and comedy that mocks God and His creation - that's not for me anymore, I'm a Christian.</li>
<li>Parties centered around alcohol and drugs - that's not for me anymore, I'm a Christian.</li>
<li>Pornography and anything related to it - that's not for me anymore, I'm a Christian.</li>
</ul>

<p>As you change your identity, you change your behavior.  Your new behavior reinforces your identity and you grow in holiness.</p>

<p>It's like those weird balls you played with in PE class that had a tail.  Your identity is the ball part.  Your desires and behaviors are the tail.  Wherever the ball is going, the tail is going to follow.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/tailball.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>This isn't some new-age psychobabble - this is the core message of the New Testament regarding how we change our behavior.</p>

<blockquote class="bible"> 
Likewise reckon ye also yourselves to be dead indeed unto sin, but alive unto God through Jesus Christ our Lord.
<cite>Romans 6:11</cite>  
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="bible"> 
That ye put off concerning the former conversation the old man, which is corrupt according to the deceitful lusts;
<cite>Ephesians 4:22</cite>
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="bible"> 
Lie not one to another, seeing that ye have put off the old man with his deeds;
<cite>Colossians 3:9</cite>
</blockquote>

<p>When you change your identity.  When you reckon yourselves dead to sin.  When put on the new man.  Then your behavior will follow that change like the tail follows the ball.</p>

<p>So, if you are struggling with some sin, a big part of overcoming that struggle is to change your identity.  To change how you view yourself.  You are not a drunk and alcoholic, you are a faithful Christian with a new heart.  You are not addicted to porn, you are addicted to Christ.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/Grocery-Store-Layout.gif" alt="" /></p>

<p>Approach life with a new identity and walk through the grocery store of life like I do as someone who eats gluten free.  A whole lot of aisles just aren't for you.  That's ok - what is down those aisles is only pain, and there is tons of good stuff left for you.</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/imagining-an-alternative-to-bible-college</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/imagining-an-alternative-to-bible-college" />
    <title>Imagining An Alternative to Bible College</title>
    <published>2022-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2022-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Ryan Hayden</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">In my last post, I talked about the problems with Bible College, and why I was glad I went there.  In this post, I want to lay out an alternative based on the conversations I&#039;ve been having with other pastors and Christians and on the changing nature of......</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>In my last post, I talked about the <a href="https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/whats-wrong-and-right-about-bible-college-and-some-tips-for-going/">problems with Bible College</a>, and why I was glad I went there.  In this post, I want to <strong>lay out an alternative</strong> based on the conversations I've been having with other pastors and Christians and on the changing nature of ministry.</p>

<p><strong>There are no Bible colleges in the Bible.</strong>  The closest thing is the school of the prophets in 1 and 2 Kings, but nothing like Bible college is mentioned, never mind prescribed, in the New Testament.</p>

<p>That means, that Bible colleges, while <em>potentially</em> good, are not <em>necessary</em> for flourishing Christian churches. It also means that, if it's not something <em>prescribed</em> in scripture, we are free to innovate and imagine alternatives to our current system.</p>

<p>What <strong>is</strong> talked about in the scripture <em>A LOT</em> is the local church.  It <strong>is</strong> <em>prescribed</em>. It <strong>is</strong> God's plan.</p>

<h2>Local Church Pastoral Training</h2>

<p>So what if, as opposed to Bible college, the work of training for the ministry was done by a local church?  What would that look like?</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>[!note]
  I'm fleshing out ideas here presented to me on twitter and facebook by others.  Special thanks goes to Stephen Burrell and Mike Bird.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Here is what I am imagining:</p>

<h3>1. A man would be identified as called to ministry.</h3>

<p>The process would start as it usually does, with a man sensing a call to service and having that calling confirmed by the church.  This man would then seek a pastoral apprenticeship either in his own church or in a an affiliated church.</p>

<h3>2. The man would undertake an extensive apprenticeship under the guidance of a local church.</h3>

<p>This pastoral student would then formally enter an apprenticeship program and agree to stay in the program for a period of several years.  The man would not have to pay for this training, but would be expected to find employment and/or housing in the community while he trained.</p>

<h3>3. The program would follow a set timeline and set curriculum.</h3>

<p>Much like a traditional Bible college, this student would have a prescribed curriculum to study.  He would be assigned reading and papers on various subjects including:</p>

<ul>
<li>Old and New Testament Survey</li>
<li>Hermeneutics</li>
<li>Bible Geography</li>
<li>Doctrine</li>
<li>Homiletics</li>
<li>Church History</li>
</ul>

<p>Instead of learning these in a classroom, he would be expected to study under the direction of the pastor/elders at his church and be tested at the end of each subject to prove his knowledge.</p>

<h3>4. The pastor would set aside multiple hours a week to mentor/guide their studies.</h3>

<p>In addition to his coursework, the student would spend time every week discussing theoretical and practical aspects of ministry with his pastor.  As problems came up in both the pastor's and the student's ministry, they would be discussed, and the apprentice would go with the pastor on hospital visits, deacon's meetings, weddings and funerals, etc..</p>

<h3>5. As his studies progress, he would be given more responsibility in the church.</h3>

<p>A big part of this apprenticeship would be serving and teaching in the church.  As the apprenticeship progressed, more and more opportunities for service would be given.  Eventually, if gifting is apparent, the student would be given an adult Sunday School class or even allowed to regularly preach during evening services at the church.  All under the watchful eye of and with the feedback of the pastor.</p>

<h3>6. Difficult subjects will be handled offsite or online courses.</h3>

<p>In depth training in difficult subjects like Greek/Hebrew could be done via online courses, or in some cases, offsite module courses.  Alternatively, a group of local pastors could identify a pastor in their midst who is gifted in these areas and he could teach a weekly night course.</p>

<h3>7. A person's studies culminate in ordination and formal recognition of his studies and gifting.</h3>

<p>At the end of the course of study (multiple years) the student/apprentice would go through a formal ordination ceremony where they would be questioned by a committee of pastors.  Afterwards, he would be encouraged to seek ministry opportunities in churches looking for a pastor.</p>

<h2>Benefits</h2>

<h3>1. Local churches wouldn't lose their best workers to Bible college.</h3>

<p>A lot of churches lose their best servant-minded young people and young adults to Bible colleges already awash with these people.  In this local church model, that wouldn't happen.</p>

<h3>2. Students would save the expense of Bible college.</h3>

<p>Bible colleges often require relocation, cost tens of thousands of dollars and years of your life.  Students in a local church would see none of those expenses, and only pay for books.</p>

<h3>3. Students would gain real-world experience under the watchful eye of a pastor.</h3>

<p>Students would get experience in ministry and behind the pulpit and would get feedback in real time from their pastor/elders.  They could also gain valuable work experience in a trade that wouldn't be possible with a traditional Bible College schedule.</p>

<h3>4. Gifting (or lack thereof) would be seen and addressed sooner.</h3>

<p>There is a reason "apt to teach" is listed as a qualification for the pastorate - some people don't have it.  Some people cannot preach.   Some who do have the ability to teach have bad speaking and study habits that need to be addressed and often aren't addressed under the current system.</p>

<h3>5. Students would get a more real-world perspective of local church ministry.</h3>

<p>Going to a mega-church to learn about ministry sometimes seems counterproductive.  Megachurches do ministry in completely different ways and often, what works for the megachurch doesn't work for normal local churches.  Students at these schools often come home thinking they know better than their faithful pastors and disdaining normal ministry.  The local church model saves them from that.</p>

<h2>Disadvantages</h2>

<p>Such a course of training would have disadvantages too.  I can think of three.</p>

<h3>1. Students may miss out of the opportunity to make friends and date potential spouses.</h3>

<p>I made many good friends in Bible college from around the country. I also met my spouse in Bible college, as did hundreds of other people in ministry.  This may be hard to replicate in a smaller church.</p>

<h3>2. Students may miss out on the opportunity to expand their horizons.</h3>

<p>I went to Bible college in Tennessee as a yankee from New Hampshire.  I experienced culture shock and met many friends from other parts of the country.  This was a good thing and expanded me as a person.  If a person is trained in the church where he grew up, he may be tempted to be a small minded person.  Local church training may result in a kind of cultural inbreeding which would do disservice.</p>

<h3>3. Local church training may be despised by future employers and churches.</h3>

<p>This scenario is best suited for some one who already has a secular degree or who is working in a trade.  If this is seen as an alternative for vocational training, it may leave the student in a place where he cannot provide for his family.</p>

<h3>4. The pastor may not be equipped to do this training.</h3>

<p>The pastor may not be well trained himself, and may not be equipped to train others.  Perhaps he disdains study and doesn't "give attendance to reading" - in that case he would be depriving a student of a good education.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>If you are reading this and are interested in this kind of ministry training, I may have a place for you at Bible Baptist.  Our church has an apartment we've talked about making available for this purpose, and it is something I've been praying about for awhile.  Talk to your pastor about it and consider reaching out.</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/whats-wrong-and-right-about-bible-college-and-some-tips-for-going</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/whats-wrong-and-right-about-bible-college-and-some-tips-for-going" />
    <title>What&#039;s wrong and right about Bible College</title>
    <published>2022-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2022-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Ryan Hayden</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">In this post, I&#039;m going to discuss what I think are the problem with Bible colleges, then discuss why I&#039;m personally grateful I went, and finally give some unsolicited advice to young people considering a Bible college.

Before I get into this, I guess I......</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <blockquote class="summary">In this post, I'm going to discuss what I think are the problem with Bible colleges, then discuss why I'm personally grateful I went, and finally give some unsolicited advice to young people considering a Bible college.</blockquote>

<p>Before I get into this, I guess I should define my terms.</p>

<p>When I say "Bible College" I have in mind a four year ministry school, usually unaccredited, usually run as a ministry of a church, where the only thing you can learn there is how to be a pastor, missionary or Christian school teacher.</p>

<p>Many of these colleges exist across denominations.  They are all over the country.  The independent Baptist movement that I'm a part of has had many, and I graduated from one of these schools.</p>

<p>I loved my time at Bible college and learned a ton there.  It was an invaluable part of my ministry preparation.  I know that experience is shared by many other pastors, missionaries and evangelists across the country.</p>

<p>So...</p>

<h2>What's wrong with Bible college?</h2>

<p>Let me start by saying that Bible College <em>can be</em> and <em>has been</em> an absolutely terrible thing for many people.  There are five main things wrong with modern Bible colleges:</p>

<p><strong>First, many impressionable young people are pressured into attending.</strong>  There is a lot of pressure in certain kind of churches for young people to attend Bible college.  Many youth conferences and camp speakers put a lot of pressure on young people to go to one of these schools.  Many pastors and parents insist that their kids go to one of these schools for at least a year.</p>

<p>This pressure keeps the lights on at the bible colleges, but it also fills the schools with many people who have no business being there, and more than a few there against their will.  When I was at Bible college I had roommates kicked out for shoplifting DVDs.  My wife had a room mate kicked out for frequenting raves and getting pregnant.  There were lots of students there because they were made to come, and their attitude and behavior reflected that.</p>

<p>I feel worse for the people pressured to come who were just <em>pleasers</em>. I think many knew they didn't need to be in Bible College but didn't want to upset anyone.  My guess is many of the people I went to school with were in this category.</p>

<p><strong>Second, many of these Bible colleges do very little teaching.</strong>  Some of these Bible Colleges seem more like a ploy to recruit workers to the church than actual places of learning.  I've met more than one Bible college graduate that couldn't define words like "hermeneutics" and "homiletics" (the two main subjects they should have been studying) or who couldn't talk intelligently about basic doctrines.</p>

<p>What do they learn in such schools?  It would seem like nothing more than an expensive experiment in brainwashing.  There has to be cheaper ways to get people to wear ugly suits, pledge allegiance to your brand of fundamentalism, and recite the same twenty mindless platitudes.</p>

<p><strong>Third, often these Bible colleges feed the ego of their founders.</strong>  It seems like some of them's main function is to make the founder seem like a "great man," provide him an opportunity to bestow meaningless degrees on his preacher-friends and thus further his personal platform.  Sometimes, and this was certainly the case for my school, the founder or president's personal preferences and quirks are given ridiculous importance.</p>

<p><strong>Four, if you attend one of these schools, you may struggle to find employment for the rest of your life.</strong>  A Bible College degree isn't worth very much outside of a very small group.  It's likely not accredited.  If you want any kind of job that requires academic credentials - you are likely going to struggle with a Bible college degree.</p>

<p>Many of the people I went to school with ended up getting a second bachelor's degree.  Essentially paying twice for college.  Many more ended up doing menial entry-level jobs (like gas station attendant or hotel night manager) to feed their families.</p>

<p><strong>Fifth,</strong> and this is not made clear enough, <strong>many Bible college graduates aren't going to find a paying job in church work.</strong>  The average church size in the US is 80. 90% of churches have less than 200 members.  Many will go on (like me) to be bi-vocational pastors.  Some will end up barely subsisting teaching in Christian schools or as assistant pastors at medium sized churches.  Many, many more will come home with a degree and learn that, even in their home church, it doesn't mean much.</p>

<p>Now, the same could be said of someone getting any number of degrees at a public university.  The old joke about the philosophy factory down the road is funny for a reason.  But literature and gender-studies majors don't labor under the pretense that God owes them success, and many Bible college students do.</p>

<p>So to sum it up, many Bible colleges use ungodly pressure tactics to get people in the door, then don't really teach them anything so that their founders can have a bigger platform for their egos.  This leaves many students either unable to support their families and many others laboring in unpaid positions.</p>

<p>Despite all this...</p>

<h2>I'm glad I went to Bible College</h2>

<p>I actually loved my Bible College experience.  I met my wife in Bible College.  I met some really good friends there.  I had some amazing memories.  I learned a lot.  I grew much closer to Christ.</p>

<p>My college, while far from academically rigorous, actually did teach and expect us to learn.  We were quizzed on books like:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Biblical-Preaching-Development-Delivery-Expository/dp/0801049121/ref=sr_1_1?keywords=biblical+preaching&amp;qid=1663854652&amp;sr=8-1">Biblical Preaching</a> by Haddon Robinson</li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Understanding-Applying-Bible-Robertson-McQuilkin/dp/0802490913/ref=sr_1_4?keywords=understanding+and+applying+the+bible+robertson+mcquilkin&amp;qid=1663854690&amp;sprefix=understanding+and+applying+the+bible%2Caps%2C112&amp;sr=8-4">Understanding and Applying the Bible</a> by Robertson McQuilken</li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Basic-Theology-Systematic-Understanding-Biblical/dp/0802427340/ref=sr_1_1?crid=9BGHDNP3FO5K&amp;keywords=basic+theology+charles+ryrie&amp;qid=1663854726&amp;sprefix=basic+theolo%2Caps%2C102&amp;sr=8-1">Basic Theology</a> by Charles Ryrie</li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Fundamentalism-American-Culture-George-Marsden/dp/0197599494/ref=sr_1_1?crid=3ABBTEFM1X9HP&amp;keywords=george+marsden&amp;qid=1663854960&amp;s=books&amp;sprefix=george+marsden%2Cstripbooks%2C136&amp;sr=1-1">Fundamentalism and American Culture</a> by George Marsden</li>
</ul>

<p>And introduced to the writings of Christian giants like:
- <a href="https://www.amazon.com/A-T-Robertson/e/B001KHLQZU?ref=sr_ntt_srch_lnk_2&amp;qid=1663854799&amp;sr=8-2">A.T. Robertson</a>
- <a href="https://www.amazon.com/J-Sidlow-Baxter/e/B001H6Q686?ref=sr_ntt_srch_lnk_3&amp;qid=1663854835&amp;sr=1-3">J. Sidlow Baxter</a>
- <a href="https://www.amazon.com/F-B-Meyer/e/B001HCU94C?ref=sr_ntt_srch_lnk_1&amp;qid=1663854865&amp;sr=1-1">F.B. Meyer</a>
- <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Charles-Haddon-Spurgeon/e/B000APSXTK?ref=sr_ntt_srch_lnk_2&amp;qid=1663854903&amp;sr=1-2">Charles Spurgeon</a>
- and many more.</p>

<p>The things I learned in Bible College are the foundational knowledge on which I've built my ministry.  Perhaps more importantly, in college <strong>I learned that what I learn in college wouldn't be enough,</strong> and that I was signing up for a lifetime of study.</p>

<p>After Bible college I went to work as a Christian school teacher at the Christian school I graduated from in New Hampshire, and after two years there, ended up spending five years working for an amazing mentor pastor in Tennessee (who pastored the same church for over 40 years.)  While in Tennessee, I took master's summer classes at another Christian College in education, and it was during those classes I really learned to study and write.</p>

<p>While in Bible College, I developed an interest in web and graphic design, and immediately after graduating, I bought a laptop and some software and started learning all I could.  For nearly ten years, I studied and took online courses during my free time.  Eventually, this hobby blossomed into a second career, and I cofounded a software company which pays my bills today.</p>

<p>About seven years after I graduated from Bible College, I got a call from a little church in a town I'd never heard of asking me to come and preach.  I wasn't looking for this, and wasn't sending out any resumes.  It was a complete surprise.  (They got my number from a past church member who was in my current church.)  After preaching there twice, they voted to have me be the next pastor, I've served as the pastor at that church for 11 years now.</p>

<p>So Bible College worked out for me.   I really believe I followed God's leading there, it was some of the best years in my life, and it truly was foundational for my life and ministry.</p>

<p>So with that in mind, here is...</p>

<h2>Some unsolicited advice for people considering Bible College</h2>

<h3>1. Make sure you are called of God.</h3>

<p>Do NOT go to a Bible college because you got caught in the Bible College industrial complex's dragnet.  Pray about it.  Pray about it outside of the hothouse influences that got you thinking about it in the first place.  Seek wise counsel from your parents and godly older men from various trades.  If you are still convinced (as I was) that Bible college is for you - then go all in.</p>

<h3>2. Consider learning a trade.</h3>

<p>Regardless of what you may think, you most likely will not be pastoring a large church.  You'll likely spend many years, if not your entire ministry, in churches that cannot pay you much.   There are many trades you can learn in a few years that would be an invaluable asset to you for the rest of your life:</p>

<ul>
<li>You can get a nursing degree.</li>
<li>You can learn to be an electrician, plumber, or HVAC technician.</li>
<li>You can learn to weld.</li>
</ul>

<p>These types of skills will always be in demand and will pay you well enough to support a family while you serve in a church.  You could either learn these trades before you go to college or while you are in college.  Some colleges (like my alma mater) now encourage ministry students to learn a trade and offer a trade school to them.</p>

<h3>3. Make sure you attend a reputable college that believes in education.</h3>

<p>There are half a dozen schools (that I know of) that I would not recommend to a teenager in my church.  In fact, I try to avoid camps and youth rallies where these schools are represented.  Most of the people who are bitter about their Bible college experience got suckered into attending one of these schools.
The best way to avoid this is to go to the school and sit in some classes.  If it isn't a good school, there will be plenty of red flags:
- Does it seem like a school or a brainwashing factory?<br />
- Are students studying books written hundreds of years ago or books written by other colleges, or are they just passing around books by the pastor and his friends?<br />
- Does the school take an anti-intellectual posture? (As crazy as that sounds, it's a thing.)</p>

<h3>4. Submit to the rules.</h3>

<p>Regardless of where you go to school, they will have rules you will not like.  My college (when I attended there) had rules forbidding shorts and wearing jeans off campus.  I had to wear a suit nearly constantly and could not grow facial hair.   I needed express permission to do things as simple as drive fifty miles away to go hiking with friends.</p>

<p>No matter how strict the rules are, determine to submit to them while you are there.  If you cannot abide the rules, go elsewhere.  But do not whine about college rules for the rest of your life.  The military (and military colleges) also have ludicrous rules for people to follow, but twitter isn't overflowing with people complaining about it.</p>

<p>No one expects you to live like that as an adult. I regularly wear shorts and jeans.  I occasionally grow facial hair.  I do all sorts of things I couldn't do in Bible college and have zero fits of conscience about it.  So go, submit, graduate and then live your life in the liberty of the gospel.</p>

<h3>5. Focus on preparation for ministry.</h3>

<p>When you go to Bible College, you should go for one thing: to prepare yourself for the ministry.  Go to get educated on how to be a pastor or missionary.  Learn all the good things you can, not just from classes but from the experience that will help sharpen your ministry. Look for opportunities to serve.  Try to minister in the summer through camps, tour groups, and internships. Dig a deep well you can draw from for the rest of your life.</p>

<h3>6. Make good friends and good memories.</h3>

<p>In college, you'll have the opportunity to make lifelong friends: avail yourself of it.  Few things will make a bigger difference in your life than the people you choose to be your friends.  Find godly people and make some memories with them.</p>

<p>Lots of people I went to school with aren't in the ministry.  Many aren't even in church. But, it's interesting that most of the people I hung out with in college are still in the ministry today.  Due to the nature of Bible College, there will be plenty of people who don't want to be there.  Avoid these people.</p>

<p>Go on activities.  Do goofy stuff with your friends.  Take trips.  As restrictive as Bible College rules are, in some way you'll have more opportunities for this kind of stuff there than at any point for the rest of your life.  So make the most of it.</p>

<h3>7. No one cares about your Bible College degree.</h3>

<p>A small number of people brag about their degree from bible college like it's a degree from Harvard.  Nothing could be sillier.  Don't be that person.</p>

<h3>8. Learn to be a lifelong learner.</h3>

<p>When I was in Bible College, I spent a lot of extra time in the library, reading books that weren't a part of my assigned course work.  My poor girlfriend (now my wife) would sit in there with me for hours as I read all kinds of things.  (I tell her now she knew what she was getting into.)</p>

<p>From about the time I was 16 until today, I've read at least two books a month that <em>do not</em> have anything directly to do with my workload at that point.  I've written about that <a href="https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/how-to-read/">here</a>.  If you are called to the ministry, then you are going to spend the rest of your life <em>teaching yourself</em>, and you'll be fitting it in between very busy weeks, so you may as well start while you are in school.</p>

<h3>9. Realize Bible College isn't a requirement.</h3>

<p>While there are hints that something <em>like</em> a Bible college existed in scripture (the school of the prophets in the Old Testament), there is nothing in the Bible that says you must attend a Bible college to be a pastor.  While there are benefits to Bible college, you <em>could</em> study underneath a pastor in a kind of pastoral apprenticeship, and it would be no less valuable.  You could also go the traditional path and get a degree outside of ministry, work for awhile, and then go to a seminary.  Bible college is just one of many legitimate ways to prepare for the ministry.</p>

<h3>10. Find a good pastor to work for, even if it's for free.</h3>

<p>If you are serious about being in the ministry, the absolute best thing you can do after you graduate is to find a seasoned pastor, someone who has been in the ministry for twenty-five plus years, and work under him for awhile.  Even if you have to work in a free capacity, you should approach this with the same seriousness you approached Bible college.</p>

<p>I know a lot of people who were burned by who they worked for after Bible college.  There is abuse that can happen here.  So be careful.</p>

<p>But in my case, I would not have been able to stay in my church for nearly 11 years now, was it not for what I learned working alongside a mentor who had pastored the same church for 40 years.  I loved Bible college, but I'd take that experience over Bible college any day.</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/why-i-manuscript</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/why-i-manuscript" />
    <title>Why I manuscript</title>
    <published>2022-09-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2022-09-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Ryan Hayden</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">In this long post, I want to explain why I&#039;m a manuscript preacher, talk about what that looks like, and give you some of my tips and tricks.  Even if you never become a manuscript preacher, if you have to preach in front of people, you may be helped by......</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>In this long post, I want to explain why I'm a manuscript preacher, talk about what that looks like, and give you some of my tips and tricks.  Even if you never become a manuscript preacher, if you have to preach in front of people, you may be helped by reading this.</p>

<h2>Terrified of Public Speaking</h2>

<p><img src="/assets/img/martin-castro-9UNuCjJnQbA-unsplash.jpg" alt="" />)
It happened again last night.  I had a nightmare about public speaking.  <em>Here is an odd truth:</em> even after preaching over a thousand sermons, even after routinely preaching high emotion funerals and leading large weddings, even after being in the ministry for close to twenty years, <em>I'm still not comfortable with public speaking</em>.  I don't think I ever will be.</p>

<p>As odd as it sounds, that may be my greatest strength as a preacher.  You see, I've given a lot of thought into <strong>why</strong> I'm not comfortable with public speaking.  I've really dug into what exactly scares me.  What's happening in those public speaking nightmares.  <strong>It boils down to four specific things:</strong></p>

<h3>1. Not knowing what to say.</h3>

<p>This is the most pressing of my terrors.  In so many of these public speaking nightmares I'm standing up in front of a crowd and <em>I have nothing</em>.  My mind is totally blank.</p>

<p>After all, I am not an unending spring of wisdom.  Like every other married man in the history of the world, very often my wife asks "what are you thinking about?" and I say, with total honesty "nothing."  What happens when you have nothing and there are 100 or more people staring at you, all expecting you to have <em>something?</em>  I don't want to find out.</p>

<h3>2. Not having enough to say</h3>

<p>A similar terror is the fear of not having <em>enough</em> to say.  I remember the first few times I was ever asked to preach as a teenager, and despite my best efforts, it was over in five minutes.  I still remember how disappointed my pastor/boss was, when as a twenty-three year old asked to fill the pulpit, I couldn't speak for longer than fifteen minutes.</p>

<p>I almost always preach now for thirty-forty minutes, but I still have a fear that I'm going to come up very short.  Too often, I've said something at the beginning of a message like "I think this is going to be a short one tonight", and while it usually isn't, this is tangible evidence of this fear coming to the surface.</p>

<h3>3. Not having enough to say, and still saying a lot</h3>

<p>Maybe a bigger fear is not having enough to say and still preaching for forty minutes.  <em>I've heard many preachers who routinely say in an hour what they should have said in fifteen minutes.</em>  I really don't want to become that kind of preacher.</p>

<p>Have you listened to one of John MacArthur's sermons lately?  Whether you like him or not, that man is 83 years old, and his sermons still have far more content than mine ever will.  But that's not <em>normally</em> how it goes.</p>

<p>What seems to happen is, that normally, as a pastor ages, they start sharing the same stories, they start inserting the same points, they start saying the same sound bites.  As they age, they become better at adding this air into their sermons.  They know they can just fall back on their hobby horses or their favorite stories - and so they do.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/mitchell-leach-DmdQGZqR_38-unsplash.jpg" alt="" />)</p>

<p>I want my sermons to be like a can of Pringles, not like a bag of Lays. I want my sermons to be full of content.  I want a thirty minute sermon to be a thirty minute sermon, not a ten minute sermon with twenty minutes of jokes, stories and air.  I'm terrified of the day I start resorting to filler.</p>

<p>Finally...</p>

<h3>4. Not staying on point</h3>

<p>I'm terrified of being all over the place.  Of being known for chasing rabbit trails and going far afield of my point.</p>

<p>My favorite preachers have always been <em>tight.</em>  They have always been the ones who I knew had a point and stayed on that point.  When they started telling a story or sharing an illustration, I knew that they knew where they were going with it.</p>

<p>I have ADHD.  I'm naturally all over the place.  I want my sermons to follow a straight line, and I'm terrified my sermons will look more like a golden retriever let loose in a busy parking lot.</p>

<h2>I'm not a great public speaker</h2>

<p>I think my fear of public speaking is further intensified by knowing that I'm not a great public speaker and likely never will be.  We all know preachers who have an unbelievable gift of presence, the Scott Pauley's and the Kenny Baldwin's, that is not, and likely never will be me.</p>

<p>I'm not a yeller.  I'm not a pew walker.  I'm not a joker.  I'm not a big, commanding presence.  I know this and I've made peace with it.</p>

<p>I remember being in Bible college and listening to the never ending array of preachers come through and thinking all along - <em>I could never do that</em>. I could never be Mr. Larger-than-life.  I could never be like Clarence Sexton or like R.B. Oullette.  That's just not me.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/zach-lucero-X4V-El4qvZ4-unsplash.jpg" alt="" />)</p>

<p>But there was one chapel speaker who came, and I believe he only came once, who changed my life.  (It was Jim Blalock, a pastor from Jupiter, Florida.)  His preaching style was so different.  He wasn't trying to keep our attention with his personality, he was keeping out attention with his content.  It was the first time I ever heard a preacher and thought both of these things at once: "man that's good", and "I think I could do that someday."</p>

<p>He happened to be a manuscript preacher.</p>

<p>I'm still terrified by extemporaneous speaking.  If I visit your church for a service, and you call me up on the fly to come up to the pulpit and say something, I will not be grateful for the opportunity, I'll probably have high blood pressure for the rest of the day.  I don't stammer much anymore, but when I do, it's almost always during the parts of the service when I have to speak off the top of my head (like during announcements or business meetings.)</p>

<h2>Pastoring is hard</h2>

<p>As a pastor, I have to preach to the same people week in and week out, for years.  There are dozens of people in my church who have been faithfully in their place to hear me preach now, three times a week, for the last 11 years.  Those poor people have heard nearly 1,500 Ryan Hayden sermons, and there is no end in sight.</p>

<p>It's really hard to preach to the same people for years and not get boring.  <strong>I'm not that interesting.</strong>  They have heard every one of my stories by this point.  They know what happened that one time I got lost in the cave.  They know the punch line to both of my jokes.</p>

<p>Further, they know me.  They know that my kids aren't perfect.  They know that I still don't have flowers in my garden patch (after living in the same house for 11 years.)  They know I'm likely to forget whatever it was they told me last week.  They've learned to roll their eyes at every new hobby.</p>

<p>Despite my obvious and abundant flaws.  Despite the other preachers in town who are quite good, and the preachers online who are excellent.  They still come to listen.  I can never take that for granted.</p>

<p>I often try to remember that when I'm speaking to 50 people for thirty minutes, that I'm not just using thirty minutes of people's time, I'm using 1,500 minutes of people's time.  People are collectively giving me more than a full day of man hours.  The day that is no longer an honor and a solemn responsibility is the day I should probably stop pastoring.</p>

<h2>Pre-preaching</h2>

<p>The main reason I  write out  my sermons is that it allows me to face my main fears - fears around content - before I stand up in front of people.  The manuscript gives me the confidence that I have enough to say, that my sermon will not be just filler, that my sermon is not the same thing I preached last month, and that I know where I'm going.</p>

<p>I don't think of my manuscript as a piece of prose, I think of it as pre-preaching.  In my mind I'm not sitting in my tiny closet office staring at a black screen.  In my mind I'm in the pulpit, and I'm preaching through my fingers.  I'm finding the dead ends and the tough spots, identifying the places where I'm going to drone on.  I'm discovering where I haven't thought through that point enough.  Where a point needs some work, or needs to be said differently.  Again, it's not manuscripting, it's pre-preaching.</p>

<p>Charles Spurgeon told his students that the golden key to keeping people's attention is to say something worth listening to.  David McCollough said "Writing is thinking. To write well is to think clearly. Thats why its so hard."  Writing out a manuscript, or pre-preaching, gives me the opportunity to be sure that I'm thinking clearly through my subject and that I'm saying something worth listening to.</p>

<p>This pre-preaching is an unfair advantage that's available to any preacher willing to put in the time.  It's an unfair advantage that only requires a few extra hours of your time, and the will to see it through.  It gets easier and faster, but it's never easy or fast - and that is a benefit.</p>

<h2>Dangers of the manuscript</h2>

<p>I don't like to think of myself as a manuscript preacher.  I'm a preacher, who happens to have a manuscript.  Of course, if I lose my train of thought, I can always pick up my notes and read - but I don't really think of what I'm doing as reading.  I'm preaching.  My notes are a guide.  But if things work the way they are supposed to, my brain finds the well-worn tracks my writing has already gone down - and I'm not bound to my notes.</p>

<p>Preaching needs earnestness.  I need to preach with authority.  The fire comes not from the tone of my voice - but from the conviction with which I speak.  The fire comes when I believe what I'm saying and when I believe that people really need to hear it.  If this is the case, there is nothing about a manuscripted sermon that makes it have any less fire than a sermon spoken extemporaneously.</p>

<p>Also, and I cannot stress this enough: <strong>A sermon needs to sound like a sermon, not like a person reading prose.</strong>  When I'm writing something to be read - like this post, I may rely on lots of parenthetical statements, or I may use some clever rhetorical tricks.  I may employ longer sentences and longer quotes - but I can never do that with a sermon.  In a sermon my vocabulary needs to be turned down, my sentences and paragraphs need to be shorter - I need to write like I'm speaking to a bunch of people listening.</p>

<p>Recently, I had a conversation about preaching with a man who attended my church for years.  I showed him my notes and explained that everything is written out.  He didn't believe it.  He said you would never know - that's a good thing.  That's what we are going for.</p>

<p>Now, let me close this already too long post with some...</p>

<h2>Tips for writing and preaching a manuscript</h2>

<p><img src="/assets/img/aaron-burden-siB9Th_Ma34-unsplash.jpg" alt="" />)</p>

<h3>1. Write like you are preaching.</h3>

<p>I've already belabored this point, but if you are going to write a manuscript, then you need to write like a speaker and not like a writer.  When we speak, we use a different vocabulary.  We use different sentence structure.  We use shorter and choppier sentences.</p>

<p>I just imagine I'm preaching as I write and try to make sure what I'm writing is something I can actually say.  Sometimes I read my notes aloud and edit the parts that I have a difficult time saying.  Remember, it's a sermon, not a book.</p>

<h3>2. Start with an outline.</h3>

<p>I like to write out what I think the passage means in a few sentences, and then write out an outline before I start working on a manuscript.  You actually do this much like you would if you were writing a research paper -</p>

<ul>
<li>you start with lots of reading and study</li>
<li>you write a thesis sentence</li>
<li>you write an outline of points supporting your thesis</li>
<li>you write the body of the paper.</li>
</ul>

<p>Writing a sermon is the same.  Only your main source is going to the be scripture and your "paper" isn't for the consumption of professors, but a sermon to be listened to by real people.</p>

<h3>3. Have a word goal.</h3>

<p>As you preach, you'll learn how many words equals a thirty or forty minute sermon.  Words count is much more valuable as a metric than pages. (Pages can be altered by format and font, your word count is your word count.</p>

<p>My word goal is to be between 2,800 and 3,200 words, but I often go as low as 2,300 and as high as 4,200.  This is going to vary greatly for you  based on your talking speed and ability to stick to your point.  So test and adjust accordingly.</p>

<h3>4. Pay attention to paragraph length.</h3>

<p>When preaching, short paragraphs are much better than long paragraphs.  Bullet points and block quotes are good.  Complicated outlines are useless.</p>

<h3>5. Plan your rest stops</h3>

<p>One of the nice things about writing out your ideas is you can be much more deliberate with diversions from your main point.  I like to try to find things that may seem like a rabbit trail, but actually further my point.</p>

<p>My favorite writer who uses this technique is Malcolm Gladwell.  He often tells stories that seem like they are totally unrelated to what he is saying, only to weave them back into the plot.    This gives people a mental break, while staying on point.</p>

<p>This is hard to describe, and even harder to pull off.   But if you can, it's so worth it.  In my opinion, it's much better to keep people's attention with well-timed and interesting anecdotes than it is with shouting and stomping.  This is only possible with a curious mind, lots of reading, good notes and absolute clarity about the point you are trying to make.</p>

<h3>6. Make your manuscript scannable.</h3>

<p>If your goal is to NOT read your notes, then they must be scannable.  Again, short paragraphs and bullet points are your friends - but so are bold and italic sentences - clear and abundant headings, and well defined breaks for scripture.</p>

<h3>7. Use writing software, not a traditional word processor.</h3>

<p>This is just my opinion, but you are doing yourself no favors when you use apps like Microsoft Word, Google Docs or Apple Pages to write your manuscript. Those apps were made for creating documents, not for writing. Instead, use a distraction free writing app.  Here are some of my favorites:</p>

<ul>
<li>Obsidian</li>
<li>Sermonly</li>
<li>Bear</li>
<li>iA Writer</li>
</ul>

<h3>8. Be careful not to just read your manuscript.</h3>

<p>Your manuscript is your guide - but you shouldn't be tied to it and should only be reading it in rare cases.  Watch a recording of yourself preaching or ask someone you trust for feedback.  Does it sound like reading or preaching?  If you are too bound to your notes, maybe read your notes through or even preach through them to an empty room.  But you aren't Jonathan Edwards - don't stand and read.  Stand and preach.</p>

<h3>9. Write names of people in the congregation in the sides of your notes.</h3>

<p>I use a mac app called Create Booklet to print my notes off as a little booklet that I bring with me to the pulpit.  Often, before the service, I'll look around the room and write the names of people who are there in the margins, purposely jumping around the room.</p>

<p>As I preach, when I come to that name, I make it a point to make eye contact with them and spend thirty seconds speaking directly to them.  In this way I'm sure to look up from the pulpit and move my gaze around the room.</p>

<h3>10. Mind the runways.</h3>

<p>I really struggle on this point.  But having a strong introduction and conclusion really make a sermon.  I'm much better at introductions than conclusions.  But if you are going going to write out two parts of a message - these should be what you focus on.</p>

<p>True to form, I didn't think of a good way to land this post.  May it's choppy ending remind you to think about how your sermon will end before you get airborne with your message.</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/a-personal-prayer-request-noah</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/a-personal-prayer-request-noah" />
    <title>A Personal Prayer Request</title>
    <published>2022-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2022-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Ryan Hayden</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">Noah went to see the dermatologists at Springfield Clinic today in Effingham.  They were incredible.  They believe he is dealing with something called CGPD.  They also think that the steroid cream he has been on is making it worse.

They prescribed new......</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <h2>Update - Tuesday, September 13</h2>

<p>Noah went to see the dermatologists at Springfield Clinic today in Effingham.  They were incredible.  They believe he is dealing with something called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Childhood_granulomatous_periorificial_dermatitis">CGPD</a>.  They also think that the steroid cream he has been on is making it worse.</p>

<p>They prescribed new treatment and promised to call at least weekly to check up.  They've already called multiple times today.</p>

<p>Also, Noah has an appointment at a pediatric nephrologists in St. Louis next Tuesday.</p>

<hr />

<blockquote class="summary">

 The last few months (especially the last few days) have been an emotional journey.  My son Noah (my only boy and the middle child of my five kids) is dealing with some mystery illness, and for a few days Amanda and I had serious concerns about cancer.  

</blockquote>

<p>![](/assets/img/IMG_4087 1.jpeg)</p>

<p>Noah is a pretty normal kid.  He swims on the swim team.  He loves riding his bike and helping me in the shop.  Besides struggling to read (we think he might be severely dyslexic) he is just like every other nine year old boy I know.</p>

<h3>Ailment 1: Eyes</h3>

<p>But last year, right before camp, we thought he had pink eye.  Only his pink eyes never went away with eye drops.  So the doctor thought he may have a scratched cornea.  But after a month that never healed.  Finally we were referred to a pediatric ophthalmologist in Champaign who quickly determined that he had something called <a href="https://my.clevelandclinic.org/health/diseases/14414-uveitis">uveitis</a>.   Basically, there was inflammation in his eyes that was causing scarring and vision loss - and were it not treated - it would continue to get worse.</p>

<p>So for the last year Noah has had (sometimes weekly) doctor appointments for his eyes (an hour drive away), and has had to take four to five eye drops multiple times a day.</p>

<h3>Ailment 2: Rash</h3>

<p><img src="/assets/img/IMG_0497.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>A few months ago, Noah started developing this rash around his mouth.  The rash did not seem to bother him and it has not responded to any treatment.  But it has continued to spread.  Now it surrounds his eyes and it's moving up his forehead and down his body.</p>

<h3>Ailment 3: Random bouts of tiredness</h3>

<p>Just as concerning for us have been periods of random bouts of extreme tiredness:</p>

<ul>
<li>After sleeping all night, he'll fall asleep for hours in the middle of the day.</li>
<li>We'll go on a normal hike (something we've done together dozens of times) and he'll stop two minutes in and you can tell he can't do it.</li>
<li>During the championship swim meet, he just curled up in a ball and slept for hours and we couldn't wake him for his events.</li>
</ul>

<p>These bouts of tiredness come and go.  For the last few weeks, he's been totally normal.  But when they come they are extreme.</p>

<h3>Ailment 4: Random vomiting</h3>

<p>Finally, he randomly gets sick and vomits.  This might happen once a month.  After throwing up he seems just fine and shows no sign of having a stomach bug.  (No loss of appetite or other symptoms.)</p>

<h2>Figuring it out</h2>

<p>So a big part of the last several months for us has been trying to figure out what is going on with our son.  We've taken him to multiple doctors: pediatrician, ophthalmologist, rheumatologist, pediatric GI doctor and they have run a bunch of tests.</p>

<p>One thing that totally enraged me was how hard it was to get him to see a dermatologist.  Even with a rash spreading across his face and body lasting for months, and even with a referral - no doctor in either of our local hospital systems would see him in less than two months.  We had to call (what felt like) every dermatologist in Illinois to get him an appointment before November.  He's sees that doctor next week.</p>

<h3>Roller Coaster Week</h3>

<p>Both the GI doctor and the rheumatologist have shown concerns about his kidneys and run a bunch of blood and urine tests.  On Wednesday, the hospital's app informed us that one of those tests came back and was very off.  Something called a <a href="https://medlineplus.gov/lab-tests/beta-2-microglobulin-b2m-tumor-marker-test/">Beta 2 Microglobulin</a> test.</p>

<p>So we googled it.   <strong>Big mistake.</strong>  Beta 2 Microglobulin is commonly used to detect blood born cancers like multiple myeloma, lymphoma and leukemia.    My biggest fear through all of this has been that Noah had leukemia, and this test seemed to confirm that.</p>

<p>We flipped out.  We couldn't get any doctor on the phone Wednesday or Thursday.  So for two days Amanda and I have been dealing with this terror.  We didn't want Noah to know about it until it was confirmed by a doctor, and we didn't want our other children to know about it - so we couldn't talk about it.</p>

<p>For two days, I've been trying to remind myself that God is in control, and that whatever His plans for us, He knows what He is doing and He is always good.  I've been trying to do what 1 Peter 5:7 says:</p>

<blockquote class="bible"> 
Casting all your care upon him; for he careth for you.
<cite>1 Peter 5:7</cite>
</blockquote>

<p>I've tried to work and do things just as I normally would, and to not worry about this.</p>

<h2>Good News</h2>

<p>Finally, about 8pm last night, the rheumatologist called.  He told us we shouldn't be concerned at this point about leukemia because that would likely show up in other ways in his blood work.  He thinks Noah might have an extremely rare disorder called <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29429748/">TINU</a> and is working on getting him in with a pediatric nephrologist in St. Louis.</p>

<p>So we went to bed last night and woke up this morning very encouraged.  We are hopeful we will get Noah into see this doctor (and the dermatologist) next week and at least begin to get this under control.</p>

<p>So, if you think about it, would you pray for Noah and pray for us as we (once again) go through this season of lots of tests and doctors appointments.</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/missionary-videos-part-2</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/missionary-videos-part-2" />
    <title>Missionary Videos - Part 2</title>
    <published>2022-09-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2022-09-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Ryan Hayden</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">So in a previous post  - I wrote about how I think the trend towards well produced Missionary Videos is a bad thing, and argued that we should go back to slide presentations.  I stand by those opinions, but there is actually a type of missionary video......</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>So in a <a href="https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/against-missionary-videos/">previous post</a>  - I wrote about how I think the trend towards well produced Missionary Videos is a bad thing, and argued that we should go back to slide presentations.  I stand by those opinions, but there is actually a type of missionary video that I think should become far more common - and that is a quick report video.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/K-_zwetSQxE" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>

<p>Here is how we do them:</p>

<h2>1. I use Calendly to schedule a fifteen minute zoom call with a missionary we support.</h2>

<p><a href="https://calendly.com/is-easy">Calendly</a> allows them to schedule a time that works for them and that fits in my schedule, without doing endless back and forth.  It also handles time zones for both of us.</p>

<h2>2. I record the zoom call using zoom's recording feature.</h2>

<p>Actually, I use <a href="https://www.ecamm.com/mac/ecammlive/">Ecamm Live</a>'s interview feature - but that is expensive software and totally overkill for this.  You could easily get by just using the zoom record feature (it's free).</p>

<h2>3. During the call, I ask the missionary to answer some questions.</h2>

<p>I try to be respectful of the missionaries time and try to make the whole thing last less than ten minutes.  Here are the questions I usually ask:</p>

<ol>
<li>Can you tell us again who you are, where you serve, and who you are serving with?</li>
<li>What does a typical week look like for you lately?</li>
<li>What current projects are you working on?</li>
<li>Do you have any prayer requests for the church?</li>
</ol>

<p>At the beginning of the call, I tell them that to answer the questions as if they are speaking to our church and I tell them it will be edited.</p>

<h2>4. I edit the video down to five minutes.</h2>

<p>For this, I simply drop the video into a video editor (you could totally use iMovie or the free version of <a href="https://www.blackmagicdesign.com/products/davinciresolve/">Davinci Resolve</a> for this) and try to edit out the small talk and get the good parts.  I then look on the missionaries facebook page and on google to find images that back up what he's saying and overlay them on the video.</p>

<p>The whole process takes me less than an hour.</p>

<h2>5. I share the video with the church in lieu of a prayer letter.</h2>

<p>During the time we would normally read a prayer letter, we watch this report from the missionary.  It's much more personal coming in his own words and backed up with photos and really helps the church connect to the missionary.</p>

<h2>Why I like this/Potential Problems:</h2>

<p>I like this because it helps our church stay connected to the missionary while taking very little of the missionary's time.  The only technological lift the missionary has to do is have a laptop or phone with an internet connection.  Almost all the work is done by me.</p>

<p>I could see how, if this became very popular - some churches could demand too much of the missionary on the field.  (I'm sure a dozen churches wanting a monthly report would get old.)  But, done in moderation, I think this really helps.</p>

<p>I know that I'm much more in tune with what is going on with the missionary and feel much more connected to their work this way and thus I'm more prone to pray for them and give a special offering towards one of their projects.</p>

<p><strong>By the way</strong> if anyone is so inclined - the missionary in the video above (<a href="https://www.facebook.com/jon.labelle.370">Jon La Belle</a>) is awesome and he's trying to raise more support.  You should definitely pray about having him in.</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/my-absolute-favorite-piece-of-software</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/my-absolute-favorite-piece-of-software" />
    <title>My Absolute Favorite Piece of Software</title>
    <published>2022-09-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2022-09-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Ryan Hayden</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">Software is a big part of my life.  I help design and build custom software at Build Online. Even if that wasn&#039;t the case, I still use software nearly all day long in my ministry.  I&#039;ve used hundreds of apps in my life and mastered many of them.

But my......</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p><img src="/assets/img/Obsidian.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Software is a big part of my life.  I help design and build custom software at Build Online. Even if that wasn't the case, I still use software nearly all day long in my ministry.  I've used hundreds of apps in my life and mastered many of them.</p>

<p>But my absolute favorite piece of software, one I think could help just about everyone, is not very well known.  <a href="https://obsidian.md">It's a cross-platform, open source note taking app called Obsidian.</a>  If I could only use one app - it would be this one.  In fact, if I could have a laptop that just had Obsidian and a browser - I could probably do 99% of my work.</p>

<p>In this post, I want to discuss how I use Obsidian as my secret weapon to get things done and why you should download it and take the plunge...</p>

<h2>How I use Obsidian</h2>

<p>I basically use Obsidian five ways:</p>

<h3>1. Obsidian is my second brain</h3>

<p>Obsidian is the one place where I dump everything:
- notes from books I'm reading
- ideas for new blog posts
- todo lists for projects
- undeveloped thoughts I have
- links to things I find interesting online
- everything else</p>

<p>To aid in this, I use <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OP3dA2GcAh8">Tiago Forte's PARA method</a> to organize my notes: PARA stands for:
- Projects - Things I'm actively working on
- Areas - Church, Business, Blog, Etc.
- Resources - Books, scripture, web links, etc.
- Archives - things I don't want to delete but don't need now. (I don't use an archive folder)</p>

<p>![](/assets/img/CleanShot 2022-09-05 at 07.06.00.png)</p>

<p>Essentially, I have four top level folders in my notes app (I've replaced the archive with an inbox folder where unprocessed notes go.)  You can actually see this at work in the sidebar on this blog - which is just a published subset of my Obsidian notes.</p>

<p>I highly recommend you read these resources if you want to get into the second brain / smart notes world:
- <a href="https://www.amazon.com/How-Take-Smart-Notes-Nonfiction/dp/B09HSSFCPR/ref=sr_1_1?crid=2BHH7DEOKXWHB&amp;keywords=how+to+take+smart+notes+snke+ahrens&amp;qid=1662379280&amp;sprefix=how+to+take+smar%2Caps%2C100&amp;sr=8-1">How to Take Smart Notes</a> - Snke Ahrens
- <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Building-Second-Brain-Organize-Potential/dp/B09MGFGV3J/ref=sr_1_1?crid=1DTHOPHME2EMH&amp;keywords=building+a+second+brain&amp;qid=1662379311&amp;s=audible&amp;sprefix=building+%2Caudible%2C83&amp;sr=1-1">Building a Second Brain</a> - Tiago Forte
- <a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL7oLu8NfQd84_gsyqBVSVgUmCCgcvSZMx">Mastering Obsidian</a> (Youtube Playlist)
- <a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/NicolevanderHoeven">Nicole Van Der Hooven</a> (Youtube Channel)</p>

<p>This is such a deep hobbit hole, you could spend years learning it - but I've found it to be extremely rewarding and helpful.</p>

<h3>Obsidian is my personal todo list / project management software</h3>

<p>Obsidian has two plugins that work in tandem I use for my ToDos:
- Obsidian Calendar
- Daily Notes</p>

<p>Basically, I have a note for each day which I keep open all day. In that daily note I put my todos, any meetings I have for that day, any links or ideas.  Obsidian's linking feature makes it easy to turn anything in this note into its own note and keep them linked.</p>

<p>![](/assets/img/CleanShot 2022-09-05 at 07.11.58.png)</p>

<p>On the topic of todos - I highly recommend the book <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Make-Time-audiobook/dp/B07DHT9BZV/ref=sr_1_1?crid=TMVCHZZ2FLHR&amp;keywords=make+time&amp;qid=1662380074&amp;sprefix=make+time%2Caps%2C93&amp;sr=8-1">Make Time</a> by Jake Knapp and John Zeratsky.  In that book, Knapp and Zeratsky advocate for a common sense strategy for keeping a todo list that I have found very helpful.</p>

<h3>Obsidian is my journal</h3>

<p>I also use my Daily notes as a journal.  If something interesting happens in a day, I'm going to write a summary of it and put it there.  If I get something special out of my devotions - it's going in my Obsidian vault.</p>

<h3>Obsidian is my place to write</h3>

<p>Obsidian is where I write.  I write sermons in Obsidian.  I write Blog Posts in Obsidian.  I even write emails in Obsidian (then copy and paste them into an email app.)</p>

<p>I've been an advocate and user of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=d8fXEhWy_rY&amp;t=695s">markdown</a> for at least 12 years and I've found Obsidian to be the perfect app for writing in markdown.  Because of this, I've moved just about everything I've written in the last decade is in my Obsidian vault.</p>

<h3>Obsidian is my blog</h3>

<p>![](/assets/img/CleanShot 2022-09-05 at 07.49.28.png)
Finally, I use Obsidian as my blog.  I pay for a plugin from the makers of Obsidian that allows me to instantly publish any note as a blog post.  This is still a fairly young publishing platform, but nothing comes close to it in terms of simplicity.</p>

<h2>Why you should use Obsidian</h2>

<p>Enough about how I use this app - here are why you should download it and play with it today:</p>

<h3>1. Obsidian is free</h3>

<p>As an open source project - <a href="https://obsidian.md">Obsidian is completely free</a>. Also, unlike other notes apps - it just uses plain text files on the file system of your computer, and doesn't try to lock you in in any way.</p>

<h3>2. Obsidian works on all kinds of devices</h3>

<p>![](/assets/img/CleanShot 2022-09-05 at 07.40.34.png)</p>

<p>Mac, PC, Linux, iOS, iPads, Android.  If you have a computer - it will probably run Obsidian.</p>

<h3>3. Obsidian is great at bi-directional linking</h3>

<p>What make Obsidian better than just a simple notes app is it's ability to do bi-directional linking and to track links between files as you move them along.</p>

<p>This means that all you have to do to link one note to another is to do double brackets &#91;&#91; and start typing the name of that note.  Then if you move that note somewhere else in Obsidian, Obsidian will automatically update that link.</p>

<p>Obsidian also gives you the really cool looking graph view to track all your notes and find relationships.
![](/assets/img/CleanShot 2022-09-05 at 07.40.03.png)</p>

<h3>4. Obsidian is flexible</h3>

<p>I think the real strength of Obsidian is just how flexible it is.  Themes allow you to make Obsidian look like anything you want and it's plugins allow you to add all kinds of functionality like:
- Calendars
- ToDos
- Databases
- Drawing
- Tables/Spreadsheets
- Slides
- Much more</p>

<p>Basically, you can make Obsidian do whatever you need it to do for you.</p>

<h3>5. Obsidian is growing</h3>

<p>One last reason to check out Obsidian is because it is growing incredibly fast.  It's only been around for a few years and is already leading the pack on note taking apps.  (Overtaking favorites like Notion, Bear and Roam Research.)  You can also find oceans of content about it on youtube and lots of people are writing themes and plugins.
![](/assets/img/CleanShot 2022-09-05 at 07.43.32.png)
The team at Obsidian is always adding new features and improving the software.  It really feels like being in on the beginning of something that is taking off like a rocket.</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/how-to-read</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/how-to-read" />
    <title>How To Read</title>
    <published>2022-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2022-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Ryan Hayden</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">As a pastor, I have to put out a huge amount of content.  Not only do I have to write three sermons every week, I deliver those sermons to the same group of people who have been listening to me crank out three sermons every week for the last eleven......</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p><img src="/assets/img/gulfer-ergin-LUGuCtvlk1Q-unsplash.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>As a pastor, I have to put out a huge amount of content.  Not only do I have to write three sermons every week, I deliver those sermons to the same group of people who have been listening to me crank out three sermons every week for the last eleven years.  My fear has always been that I would become boring, and that I would end up telling the same stories over and over again and that my sermons would eventually be just a bunch of my favorite sound bites and platitudes.</p>

<p>The only ways I know to combat that are:
- Study well
- Write out each sermon
- Read a ton of books</p>

<p>In this post I want to give you ten tips for that third item.</p>

<p>In addition to Bible reading and anything I'm reading for sermons (like commentaries), I've read at least two books each month since I was seventeen years old.  I'm convinced that, if anybody finds me interesting or convincing, this habit is probably a big part of it.</p>

<p>So here are ten quick tips on how to read more:</p>

<h2>1. Invest in reading.</h2>

<p><strong>I spend a ton of money on reading, and I consider all of the money money well spent.</strong>  Just as I wouldn't begrudge a finish carpenter spending money on his truck and his tools - books are my tools.  I probably spend between $50 and $100 per month on reading and I have always spent money on books - even when I was a poor college student.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/erick-chevez-TjBhqTqkxew-unsplash.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Currently I have the best Amazon Kindle they make (<a href="https://www.amazon.com/All-new-Kindle-Oasis-now-with-adjustable-warm-light/dp/B07FJ91TLB/ref=sr_1_3?crid=1F0QDNPZNEYP0&amp;keywords=kindle+oasis&amp;qid=1662123145&amp;sprefix=kindle+oasis%2Caps%2C127&amp;sr=8-3">the Kindle Oasis</a>).  At $350, it's a very expensive E-reader - but it works very, very well.  Unlike other e-readers, it's fast, it's waterproof, it has physical buttons for turning the pages and it has plenty of space for my huge ebook library.  While I do like physical books, the kindle lets me carry my entire library with me wherever I go.</p>

<p>I also have paid for a monthly <a href="https://www.audible.com">Audible</a> subscription ($15/mo) and I pay ($8/mo) for a service called <a href="https://readwise.io">Readwise</a>. (More on these later.)</p>

<h2>2. Follow your interests.</h2>

<p>I read all kinds of books:  I read about history.  I read about science.  I read a lot of business books.  I read books about computer programming.  I read biographies.  I read memoirs. I read classic novels.  I read thriller novels.  I read self-help books.  I read true crime stories.  I read ministry books.</p>

<p>Basically, if I'm interested in it, I read it.  I don't think it's really possible to read a lot over many years if you aren't interested in what you are reading.</p>

<h2>3. Read many books at a time.</h2>

<p>At any given time, I'm probably reading five books and have five more on deck.  If I get bored with one book, I just pick up another and then come back to that one later.  I know this doesn't work for everybody, but my brain is very good at switching channels and then coming back to where I left off.</p>

<p>Spurgeon said "Change in labour is recreation" and I heartily agree.  I rarely make myself keep reading something, and if I just can't get into a book, I may lay it aside indefinitely.</p>

<p>On that note, <strong>when it comes to books, I'm a proud quitter.</strong>  Most of the good stuff in a book is in the beginning anyways.  So if I get halfway through a book and it starts getting boring, I usually lay it aside.</p>

<h2>4. Read in small bursts.</h2>

<p>A lot of people don't read because they think they need hours alone sitting in a brown leather armchair by a fireplace in a wood paneled study.  I have five kids and two jobs.  The only time I get uninterrupted alone time is when I'm away traveling or when I'm super sick.</p>

<p><strong>95% of my reading sessions probably last less than five minutes.</strong>  The trick is to get many of them in a day.  There are probably a half dozen times a day when I get just a few minutes to read.  Times like:
- Between meetings.<br />
- While I'm waiting on a train.<br />
- When I'm standing in line.
- When I'm feeding my infant a bottle.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/dan-preindl-ZK3aBTTUzh0-unsplash.jpg" alt="" />
Those little times add up.  In order to make this happen, you have to...</p>

<h2>5. Keep a book handy always.</h2>

<p>I am almost never without either my Kindle, my iPad or my Phone and I read on all three devices.  I am also a big fan of audiobooks.  If I'm driving somewhere, I'm listening to an audiobook.  On my daily walk, I listen to an audiobook.  If I have to sweep the floor or I'm helping cook dinner, I listen to an audiobook.</p>

<p>If that book is really good, I'll sometimes buy the kindle version too, so I can...</p>

<h2>6. Take smart notes.</h2>

<p>Every preacher or writer should have a note system where they track and digest what they are reading.  I highly recommend you read the books <a href="https://www.amazon.com/How-Take-Smart-Notes-Nonfiction/dp/B09HSSFCPR/ref=sr_1_1?keywords=how+to+take+smart+notes+snke+ahrens&amp;qid=1664799969&amp;qu=eyJxc2MiOiIyLjcyIiwicXNhIjoiMi41MyIsInFzcCI6IjIuNTcifQ%3D%3D&amp;sprefix=how+to+take+sma%2Caps%2C128&amp;sr=8-1">How to Take Smart Notes</a> by Snke Ahrens and <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Building-Second-Brain-Organize-Potential-ebook/dp/B09LVVN9L3/ref=tmm_kin_swatch_0?_encoding=UTF8&amp;qid=1664799998&amp;sr=1-1">Building a Second Brain</a> by Tiago Forte.  In my case, I use an app called <a href="https://obsidian.md">Obsidian</a> as my second brain.</p>

<p>![](/assets/img/CleanShot 2022-09-02 at 08.39.00.png)</p>

<p>Obsidian is where I:
- Write my sermons
- Write these blog posts
- Keep track of my daily todos and meetings
- Take meeting notes
- And process what I'm reading or listening to.</p>

<p>To help with that last one, I pay for a service called <a href="https://readwise.io">readwise</a>.  Readwise does two simple things for me I'm willing to pay for:
- It syncs all of my Kindle highlights with my Obsidian vault.
- It sends me a daily email with five random things I've highlighted in the past.</p>

<p>But there is more to taking smart notes than just saving your highlights.  You have to summarize what you read in your own words, you have to think about how you might use that thing you learned later, and you have to store it in a way that you can access it when you need it.  This is way out of the scope of this article.</p>

<h2>7. Make friends who read.</h2>

<p>Reading is a lot more fun when you have people you can talk about it with.  I'm fortunate to work every day with several people who read.  <a href="https://twitter.com/lukeallenmiller">Luke Miller</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/danirmler">Dan Irmler</a> in particular are always recommending books and we have very similar interests.  Even if I don't tell them about it, if I'm reading something, they usually are too and we often have great conversations about what we are reading.  I also have missionary and pastor friends who are always recommending books and I appreciate those recommendations.</p>

<h2>8. Follow footnotes</h2>

<p>Another great way to find things to read is to follow footnotes.  If I like something I'm reading, but want to go deeper and understand where the author's ideas came from - I usually look at his footnotes or end notes.  Some of the most interesting books I've read I found this way.</p>

<h2>9. Give yourself an escape valve</h2>

<p>Here is a confession: sometimes I read junk on purpose.</p>

<p>Sometimes I'll read young adult fiction.  I'll say I'm reading it so I know what the kids are into, but in actuality it's just fun and gives my brain a break.  Sometimes I like to read spy novels or humor books (like Dave Barry.)</p>

<p>I find that reading fiction has the added benefit of coloring my speech.  If all you read is commentaries - you'll start to sound like a commentary and nobody wants to have a conversation with a commentary while they are roasting their smores.</p>

<p>Finally...</p>

<h2>10. Turn off the TV.</h2>

<p>You do not have unlimited time.  So if you are going to read a lot, you have to let something else go.  For me, that is TV.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/possessed-photography-HWhR6lbn5xU-unsplash.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>About the only time I watch TV is with my wife before we go to bed.  Currently, we are working through early seasons of NCIS and I usually fall asleep five minutes into the show.  (I see enough to get the gory part, but not enough to find out the resolution of the story, I wander what this does to my dreams.)</p>

<p>I love sports, but I prefer to watch the key plays or read a summary and then once or twice a year I'll set aside some time to watch a full game.</p>

<p>Basically, you can either watch a lot of  TV, or you can read a lot - but you can't do both.</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/on-pants</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/on-pants" />
    <title>On Pants</title>
    <published>2022-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2022-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Ryan Hayden</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">This week, on my twitter, one of the guys I follow said this:

Not once has the Holy Spirit instructed a preacher to speak a sermon against a woman wearing pants.&amp;mdash; Nathanael Beasley (@savedavenger) August 29, 2022



As you can imagine, all forms......</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p><img src="/assets/img/a65-design-1eJVSUfT5yA-unsplash.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<h1>culture #women #gender #dress</h1>

<p>This week, on my twitter, one of the guys I follow said this:</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Not once has the Holy Spirit instructed a preacher to speak a sermon against a woman wearing pants.</p>&mdash; Nathanael Beasley (@savedavenger) <a href="https://twitter.com/savedavenger/status/1564240929078366212?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">August 29, 2022</a></blockquote>

<script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

<p>As you can imagine, all forms of nonsense and hilarity ensued.  Because I cannot stay out of it, I decided to comment, and because I'm a total glutton for punishment, I've decided to write a blog post on what I think about the topic.  So here is what I think about women wearing pants:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I don't think about women wearing pants.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That's it.  It's such a ridiculous thing to argue about.  It's a topic I sincerely wish we could move on from.  In my own pastoral ministry, I've tried really hard to kill the topic with silence for the last ten years, but because the topic seems immune to that treatment, here I go...</p>

<p>When I think of the "pants issue" I usually try to acknowledge three truths:</p>

<h2>1. The Bible gives clear instructions on how women should dress.</h2>

<p>This is so obvious, and the examples so abundant, it should be beyond controversy.  Passages like Deuteronomy 22:5, 1 Corinthians 11:4-15, 1 Timothy 2:9-10 and 1 Peter 3:1-6 (among others) make it very clear that God expects women to dress differently than men.  It's important to note that these scriptural arguments were not made based on then current culture - but were predicated on God's creation order and on the nature of God.</p>

<p>You don't have to be a crazy fundamentalist to understand that the Bible teaches:
1. Women should dress differently than men.  They should not dress in a way that identifies them with rebellion against their created gender.
2. Women (like men) should not draw undue attention to themselves with their clothes, hair and jewelry. 
3. Women should be careful in particular not to draw sexual attention from men.</p>

<p>In my opinion, that the Bible teaches these principles is (to borrow a phrase from Paul) "without controversy."  What isn't "without controversy" is how these principles are to be applied in the life of a church-going lady in the year of our Lord 2022.</p>

<p>To help with that, I try to remind myself that</p>

<h2>2. We are living in a time that is historically novel.</h2>

<p>For almost all of human history, two things were true:
1. Clothing was both expensive and incredibly hard to produce.
2. Culture protected and recognized the distinct role of women in society.</p>

<p>But we live in a time, perhaps the first time in human history, where both of those things are no longer true.</p>

<h3>The Industrial Revolution</h3>

<p><img src="/assets/img/1280px-Elderlyspinnera.jpg" alt="" />
In the 1800s, the industrial revolution made clothing far cheaper to create.  New inventions made the farming and refinement of cotton a hundred times less labor intensive and 100 times more profitable.  Factories spread across the country that took that cotton and produced cloth in unheard of quantities.  Suddenly, instead of clothes being something that you have to laboriously produce in your home with a spindle or a needle and thread - clothing became something you could just order out a Sears catalog.</p>

<p>The globalization of the last 50 years has taken that trend and put it on steroids, giving us a dizzying array of inexpensive clothing that would have been unheard of for people at any time in history before the day before yesterday.  150 years ago, I would have been prosperous to own four pairs of pants and two good suits.  Today, both my wife and I have walk-in closets and we struggle to keep them from overflowing.  150 years ago, the options for the kind of clothing would have been extremely limited.  Today, we can log onto Amazon and find dozens of cuts of dresses, skirts, pants and jeans and we can have them on our doorstep for very little money in two days time.</p>

<h3>The Sexual Revolution</h3>

<p>The industrial revolution by itself would be historically disruptive and would confuse the clothing debate, but added to it was the sexual revolution of the 1900s.  The conveniences of modernity made the traditional job of motherhood and keeping a home far easier.  The birth control pill (and legal abortion) that came out in the 1960s made it possible for women to control the one thing keeping them out of the workplace.  Second wave feminism successfully pushed women into places they had never been before.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/The_Feminine_Mystique.jpeg" alt="" /></p>

<p>By the time I came around in the 1980s, divorce rates were sky-high.  Almost all women worked outside of the home and pants were no longer seen as an edgy statement - they were what my grandma wore around the house.</p>

<p>Now, I'm not going to pretend that second wave feminism was a good thing or that it  aligned with biblical values.  I'm merely saying that <em>it happened</em>, and it was so successful in deconstructing societal norms that what would have been absolutely scandalous and edgy for women to wear 100 years ago doesn't even raise an eyebrow today.</p>

<h3>The ladies folding Bibles</h3>

<p><img src="/assets/img/F9610911-3347-458F-A74E-CF94990CFB5C_1_105_c.jpeg" alt="" /></p>

<p>So today (literally today) I walked from my home office to the church fellowship hall, where a bunch of extremely godly women in their 60s, 70s and 80s were putting together Bibles to send to missionaries.  (They do this every Thursday.)  90% of them were wearing pants.  If I hadn't have been writing this, I wouldn't have thought twice about it.</p>

<p>Some of these ladies know the Bible better than me.  Not one of them is even a bit masculine.  Most have dedicated their lives to their homes and their husbands.  I know lots of women who only wear skirts - and if you were to put both groups in a balance - I'd take the crew folding Bibles any day.</p>

<h2>3. We should extend grace and liberty as Christians try to figure this out.</h2>

<p>So here is my take, given the fact that the Bible clearly teaches distinction and modesty in dress, and given the fact that our historical moment has made such a complicated mess of that, and given the fact that "what pertains to a man" depends a lot on where and when you were born and what your momma wore around the house - I fall back on this passage:</p>

<blockquote class="bible"> 
Let not him that eateth despise him that eateth not; and let not him which eateth not judge him that eateth: for God hath received him.
Who art thou that judgest another mans servant? to his own master he standeth or falleth. Yea, he shall be holden up: for God is able to make him stand.
<cite>Romans 14:3-4</cite></blockquote>

<p>I'm not going to say that someone who lived in the 60s or 70s who was on the front lines of the culture war and who preached against women wearing pants was wrong.  I'm going to be understanding of the people in my church who hold that standard for themselves.  But personally, it's not how I'm going to live out the Bibles principles in my own family and with my own daughters.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Let every man be fully persuaded in his own mind.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In my mind, when God's word says...</p>

<blockquote class="bible"> 
The woman shall not wear that which pertaineth unto a man, neither shall a man put on a womans garment: for all that do so
are abomination unto the LORD thy God. 
 
<cite>Deuteronomy 22:5</cite>
</blockquote>

<p>...it makes a whole lot more sense that the "abomination" was referring to people like Bruce Jenner or Ellen Page, or to the small army of gender-bending 20 something copycats stocking shelves at my Walmart - than my twelve year old daughter's floral print jeans, but if you want to disagree, that's between you and God, we are still brothers (or sisters) in Christ.</p>

<h2>Aftermath</h2>

<p>I have never, not even one time, preached a message against women wearing pants.  It's never even been hinted at in one of my sermons, but if you were to come to my church any given Sunday - you'd find that 90%  (maybe 98%) of the women were wearing modest dresses.  I've visited many churches where the pastor has a similar view on the issue, and found the same thing to be true there.</p>

<p>There are those who say this is a slippery slope, that to throw out this standard is to throw out all standards.  I just don't buy that.  Despite my position, the women in my church are careful to dress modestly and in my own life, I rarely go a week without telling my daughters to change and we are actively teaching them to be modest in the way they dress.  When missionaries or local friends come around who we know make this a big priority, we voluntarily adopt their standard.  It's not a big deal.</p>

<p>At the same time, I've known many Christians that put this issue up there in importance with the salvation by grace through faith.  I've heard heartbreaking stories from more than one godly friend who was cut off from their family over this issue.  And to be honest, I know a lot of judgmental, somewhat ignorant people who use this issue as a crutch for their self-righteousness, and I've known more than a few of these people to end up in jail for sexual perversion.</p>

<blockquote class="bible"> 
Unto the pure all things
are pure: but unto them that are defiled and unbelieving
is nothing pure; but even their mind and conscience is defiled. 
 
<cite>Titus 1:15</cite>
</blockquote>

<p>So I'm not thinking about pants.  It's not even on my radar.  I'll respect any position you take on it, so long as you do it honestly and respect my ability to do the same.</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/on-being-a-bi-vocational-pastor</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/on-being-a-bi-vocational-pastor" />
    <title>On Being Bi-Vocational</title>
    <published>2022-08-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2022-08-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Ryan Hayden</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">My path into bi-vocational ministry wasn&#039;t a normal path:

I used to look down on bi-vocational ministry...

Early in my ministry, my wife and I were looking for a church to minister in as a &quot;youth pastor.&quot;  Several churches contacted us looking for our......</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p><img src="/assets/img/ben-white-mO9vKbG5csg-unsplash.jpg" alt="" />
My path into bi-vocational ministry wasn't a normal path:</p>

<p><strong>I used to look down on bi-vocational ministry...</strong></p>

<p>Early in my ministry, my wife and I were looking for a church to minister in as a "youth pastor."  Several churches contacted us looking for our help that we would have loved to work in, but we declined because they were not "full time" positions.</p>

<p>When I became a "senior pastor" I was paid full time for the first eight years.  I never had any intention of being a bi-vocational pastor and if I was being 100% honest with myself, I probably looked down the ones that I knew.</p>

<p>But I had a hobby of developing software and that hobby (combined with some ignorant decisions) left me in debt I wasn't going to be able to repay on a small church pastor's salary.  So I started doing software projects for business clients.  One thing led to another, and before long, I was being paid for full time work, and not long after that, I was co-owner of a profitable and growing software development agency.</p>

<p>At the same time, my family was growing.  My church desperately needed to save for a new building, and I wanted to bring on more help at the church.  I went to our deacon board and asked them to stop paying me.  They declined.  The compromise we came up with was that the church would pay $1,000 per month to me and any other staff member who worked on a bi-vocational basis.</p>

<p>And so I became a bi-vocational pastor and have been now for three years.  In that time my church has grown both spiritually and numerically.  We have bought more property (debt free).  We've been able to take on interns.  I feel like our church is much healthier today than when I was "full time."</p>

<p>Bi-vocational ministry is not without it's drawbacks:<br />
- I am, just preaching two-three times a week, at the limits of my capacity.
- Sometimes I'm not available and have to reschedule with people.
- When a new ministry starts at my church - I CANNOT lead it.<br />
- Sometimes I get overwhelmed and exhausted.
- I'm not out knocking doors and I rarely have time to go to preacher meetings.</p>

<p>But on the whole, I feel like bi-vocational ministry has been good for me and my church.  So I wanted to write about the benefits of bi-vocational ministry and give you some tips I've used to make it work.</p>

<h2>The benefits of bi-vocational ministry</h2>

<p>The first benefit is an obvious one: <strong>freedom</strong>.  Because my salary isn't tied to the church, it completely changes my relationship to the church.</p>

<p>When you are "full time" there may be some people who feel like they own you and own your time.  That isn't the case when you are bi-vocational.  People understand you have to work.</p>

<p>But I'm also free to make more money.  I have five children.  We homeschool.  We have family that lives across the country that need to be visited with some regularity.  My kids do sports.  They are going to go to college soon.  Living on a full-time small church salary is really hard.</p>

<p>It frees me from worrying about whether I'm going to offend a big giver.  (Not that I even know who they are.)  It frees me to know that my salary isn't dependent on keeping the church growing.  It frees me from having to choose between a raise I know I need and something my church needs.</p>

<p>The second benefit is <strong>giving</strong>.  Because I'm free to make money, I'm also free to give more.  It's been a joy over the last few years to be able to personally give to help people I know are struggling, instead of just giving the church's money away.</p>

<p>Being bi-vocational also helps me stay and minister in a smaller church context.  Without bi-vocational ministry, I could see myself moving on to a bigger church not because of the call of God, but because of financial pressure.  My church is very debt-averse and needs to build (our auditorium barely holds 100 people) but it would likely never happen if 60% of our offerings were going to pay my salary.</p>

<p>But being bi-vocational has also enabled me to give the gift of bi-vocational ministry to other gifted ministers in our church.  We have a youth pastor and a music pastor and are able to pay both of them the same thing the church pays me.  They both work and minister in our church just as I do.  We are praying about taking on interns for a year or two after college, helping them find employment locally and paying them the same.  None of this would be possible without bi-vocational ministry.</p>

<p>The third benefit is <strong>respect</strong>. As a bi-vocational pastor my church knows why I am here - and it's not for money.  They know I'm here to give and not to get.</p>

<p>I also feel like I command more respect from successful people. When I was "just a pastor" I felt awkward talking to successful men.  Like I was somehow inferior.  (I know this is wrong, I'm just being honest.)   That is no longer there.</p>

<p>A final benefit is <strong>insight</strong>.  I know what it's like to come to church after a long day of work because I do it.  I know how hard it is to do work, church, and family time because I do it.  I have so much more appreciation for my church member's time than I did before, and I have so much gratitude for those who voluntarily give of their time every week to help in the church.</p>

<h2>Tips for bi-vocational ministry</h2>

<p>Bi-vocational ministry is HARD.  But most things in life worth doing are hard.  I'm still figuring it out, but here are some of the things we do to make it work:</p>

<p><strong>First, it's absolutely essential that you have good study and writing habits.</strong>  It's incredibly hard to preach to the same people week in and week out, multiple times a week.  You have to learn to be efficient and disciplined in your study and to carve out time for it every day.  I would suggest that, if possible, you master this BEFORE you try to take on bi-vocational ministry.</p>

<p><strong>Second, you need a job that is flexible.</strong>  I have an ideal job - I work remotely and I set my own schedule.  If you are trying to pastor and be a doctor on call at the hospital, or a you have to work construction and your boss expects you to stay late six days a week - you are going to struggle.  While it's not easy - it's probably best to find work that you own, either in some freelance capacity or by starting your own business.</p>

<p><strong>Third, you need a team.</strong>  As I've already said, at our church we have a bi-vocational team.  Everyone gets a $1,000 per month stipend.  We also couldn't do it without a lot of volunteers.  Our deacons are deacons indeed and they really help serve our church and allow me to use my small amount of time to minister.</p>

<p><strong>Fourth, you have to drop the hero complex.</strong>  Some pastors want to do everything themselves.  The slides.  Mowing the grass.  Folding the bulletins.  You won't be able to pull that off in bi-vocational ministry.  Give those blessings to others and relax your standards a bit.</p>

<p><strong>Finally, you need a personal sabbath.</strong>  You have to take time to rest and recharge your batteries.  For me, that is Friday from about 7pm to Saturday at about 7pm. (Which happens to correspond with the jewish sabbath.)  I'm not doing anything during that period of time besides resting and spending time with my family.  I usually go for a hike with my kids or teach my son something in the wood shop. My church family knows that time is sacred and with rare exceptions (like weddings and funerals) that I'm not available during that time.</p>

<p>When I was running marathons I learned that resting was as important as running.  Bi-vocational pastoring is a marathon - and you need to prioritize rest.</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/soft-gnosticism-the-fever-of-modern-christianity</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/soft-gnosticism-the-fever-of-modern-christianity" />
    <title>Soft-Gnosticism - the Fever of Modern Christianity</title>
    <published>2022-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2022-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Ryan Hayden</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">What if I told you that an ancient heresy that the apostle John fought against is now mainstream in the American church?   I believe modern Christianity is suffering from a fever I call soft-Gnosticim, and most of the time we don&#039;t even know it.



Here......</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p><img src="/assets/img/kelly-sikkema-RmByg5kFfQg-unsplash.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>What if I told you that an ancient heresy that the apostle John fought against is now mainstream in the American church?   I believe modern Christianity is suffering from a fever I call soft-Gnosticim, and most of the time we don't even know it.</p>

<h2>Ancient Gnosticism</h2>

<p>Here is wikipedia's summary of gnosticism:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Gnosticism is a collection of religious ideas and systems which coalesced in the late 1st century AD among Jewish and early Christian sects. These various groups emphasised personal spiritual knowledge (gnosis) above the orthodox teachings, traditions, and authority of religious institutions. Viewing material existence as flawed or evil, Gnostic cosmogony generally presents a distinction between a supreme, hidden God and a malevolent lesser divinity (sometimes associated with the Yahweh of the Old Testament) who is responsible for creating the material universe. Gnostics considered the principal element of salvation to be direct knowledge of the supreme divinity in the form of mystical or esoteric insight. Many Gnostic texts deal not in concepts of sin and repentance, but with illusion and enlightenment.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So, the Gnostics were a group of ancients that basically believed two things:
- The material world is bad and the spiritual world is good.
- Salvation can be found only through secret spiritual knowledge and a higher spiritual experience.</p>

<p>During the early church years, they infiltrated Christian churches and started teaching that Christ did not have a body (because bodies are bad) and that only through there secret teaching and spiritual experiences could true Christian enlightenment be reached.  This is why John said things like:</p>

<blockquote class="bible"> 
And every spirit that confesseth not that Jesus Christ is come in the flesh is not of God: and this is that
spirit of antichrist, whereof ye have heard that it should come; and even now already is it in the world. 
 
<cite>1 John 4:3</cite>
</blockquote>

<p>If you've ever wondered why there is such an emphasis on Christ coming <em>in the flesh</em> it is because they were fighting against this particular heresy.  Of course, if the material world is bad, then the enjoyment of the material world is bad too, which is probably why Paul warned about false teachers who would do things like:</p>

<blockquote class="bible"> 
Forbidding to marry,
and commanding to abstain from meats, which God hath created to be received with thanksgiving of them which believe and know the truth. 
 
<cite>1 Timothy 4:3</cite>
</blockquote>

<p>And why Paul emphasised things like this:</p>

<blockquote class="bible"> 
For every creature of God
is good, and nothing to be refused, if it be received with thanksgiving: 
 
<cite>1 Timothy 4:4</cite>
</blockquote>

<p>Because the goodness of the material world was under attack by these heretics who believed that the material was bad and the spiritual was good.</p>

<h2>Gnosticism in the church</h2>

<p>I believe gnosticism never went away, and that it has metastasized in our churches, and we don't  even realize we are carrying around these heretical tumors.  Let me give you just a few examples:</p>

<h3>Teaching on the body, soul, spirit</h3>

<p>Growing up in church and in Bible college, I was often told to draw a circle, with another circle within it, and a third circle in that.  I was told that we were made triune with a body soul and spirit, as God is triune.  That the outside circle represents the body, the middle circle represents the soul, and the inner circle represents the spirit.  Then I was taught to evaluate things by whether they appealed to my body, soul or spirit.  Things that appealed to my spirit were good, things that appealed to my body were bad.</p>

<p>![](/assets/img/soft gnostic.jpg)</p>

<p>The problem is this isn't what the Bible teaches.  The Bible teaches that God made everything for us to enjoy and that all of His creation (the physical world) is good.</p>

<p>A natural extension of this was some teaching against...</p>

<h3>Contemporary music</h3>

<p>We were taught that one of the problems with contemporary music is that it makes our foot tap.  It appeals to the flesh.   But is it bad for something to appeal to the flesh?  Lots of food appeals to my flesh, and God made it to be enjoyed with thanksgiving.</p>

<p>I think there are legitimate arguments to be made against using contemporary music in church - but this is just a lazy version of soft-Gnosticism.</p>

<h3>Embarrassment about sex and marriage.</h3>

<p>Do you know what else appeals to my flesh?  Marriage appeals to my flesh.  God designed it to appeal to my flesh and calls it "a good thing" and "honourable" in multiple passages.</p>

<blockquote class="bible"> 
Marriage
is honourable in all, and the bed undefiled: but whoremongers and adulterers God will judge. 
 
<cite>Hebrews 13:4</cite>
</blockquote>

<p>God designed our sexual desires to create families and strengthen our marriages.  But if we have a gnostic view of the world and our bodies, we can be made to feel guilty for things God called very good and wholesome.</p>

<p>All of this pours over into our experience of church where we have an...</p>

<h3>Emphasis on personal experiences over doctrine</h3>

<p>Nearly everything about the modern evangelical/fundamentalist church is about <em>experience.</em>  The music we sing talks about mystic experiences with Christ:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>[!song]
  And He walks with me, And He talks with Me
  And He tells me I am His own
  And the joy we share as we tarry there
  None other has ever known</p>
</blockquote>

<p>What is that?  Where do we see it in the New Testament?</p>

<p>This stuff is subtle, but when you start to see it, you see it everywhere:</p>

<ul>
<li>When someone talks about their "quiet time" as if God is supposed to audibly speak in his heart every day.</li>
<li>When someone says "God showed up today" what does He mean? He's talking about an experience, about a feeling.</li>
</ul>

<p>It's all a form of soft-Gnosticism that elevates experience over doctrine, feelings over faith, and makes our entire religion both subjective and just out of reach.  And nowhere is it codified more than in the system I'd call...</p>

<h3>Modern revivalism</h3>

<p>So much of modern baptist Christianity is based on this idea that we need to work up an inner religious experience.  If we could just pray longer, if we could just sing down the Spirit, if we could just have the organist play one more stanza of "Just As I Am."  This system sets sanctification as something to be obtained by serial crisis.  It's why so much emphasis is placed on "the altar call" in some of our churches.</p>

<p>In its weirdest form, "Revival" becomes an object of worship and true revival is always just out of reach.  Never mind the fact that "revival" doesn't appear once in the New Testament (either in word or in concept.). Never mind the fact that the entire system isn't found in scripture and is totally manmade.  Never mind the fact that it's all a distraction from what the Bible does prescribe.</p>

<p>Revival makes us feel good, revival is what we know, so play another verse.</p>

<h2>Breaking the fever</h2>

<p>What would it look like if you divorced your church from this soft-Gnosticism?  What if you can break the fever and come back to a normal temperature?  I'm still working through this in my own life and ministry, but here are some preliminary findings:
- You are free to focus on the doctrine found in scripture, and you do not feel the need to make every service into a crisis of faith.
- You are free from the guilt of never achieving "revival."
- You don't have to feel like a second class Christian because you have never reached the elusive "higher life."
- You can focus on just doing what God says and walking with Him every day.  Reading the scripture, spending time in prayer, shaping your life, family and church with godly habits.
- You aren't guilty about enjoying the good physical things of life, and can enjoy what God has given you with thanksgiving.
- Your focus shifts from yourself to the gospel.</p>

<p>The best spiritual Tylanol I know to break this fever is just the New Testament.  Try to stop reading it through the lens of your religious traditions and just read it. Live in it.   It may take years, but I think the fever will break, and when it does you'll realize the daze you have been in.</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/why-we-cant-be-neutral-on-political-and-cultural-issues</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/why-we-cant-be-neutral-on-political-and-cultural-issues" />
    <title>Why we can&#039;t be neutral in the culture wars</title>
    <published>2022-08-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2022-08-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Ryan Hayden</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">In my ten years of pastoral ministry in a small town in Illinois, I&#039;ve gone from avoiding anything even remotely political, to looking for reasons to attack woke/leftist ideology.  In this post I want to explain why I&#039;ve made this deliberate change:......</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>In my ten years of pastoral ministry in a small town in Illinois, I've gone from avoiding anything even remotely political, to looking for reasons to attack woke/leftist ideology.  In this post I want to explain why I've made this deliberate change:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/hannah-voggenhuber-v3NwUMmQRHQ-unsplash.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<h2>First, some background...</h2>

<p>I grew up in southern New Hampshire, which is ground zero for presidential primary politics.  My first paying regular job was working as an intern in Dan Quayle's presidential campaign (I mostly did database work.)  I devoured talk radio and political writing, and saw myself becoming a professional political campaign worker and maybe a political writer or talk radio show host.  Then I was called to the ministry.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/635986457740622183-Quayle99.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>After college I became <em>purposely non-political.</em>  I was particularly uncomfortable with the way many Christians talked about Barack Obama.  Though he was a man I voted against twice and someone whose policies I deeply disagreed with, it seemed like I was watching people I knew radicalize in real time and lose any sense of Christian bearing.  (Obviously, Trump didn't help this trend.)</p>

<p>When I became a pastor, I deliberately avoided any talk of politics in my sermons and when it did come up, it almost always came up as a warning against the excesses of the right (who remain my crowd.)  I thought then (as I do now) that most of the people in my congregation are tempted to consume a constant diet of cable news and talk radio - and that that isn't healthy.  If I ever said something critical of a politician from the left, I was also careful to "balance" it with something critical of a politician from the right.</p>

<p>I think this attitude probably describes a lot of pastors in my generation (I'm 39.)  We are uncomfortable with the way the boomers (and to a lesser extent Gen X) has done politics, and we want to distance ourself from it as much as possible.  <strong>I also think that this is a blind spot and a weakness, and it is a tactic that needs to be abandoned.</strong>  Let me explain why:</p>

<h2>1. The left is attacking foundational truths of God's word and God's order.</h2>

<p>The left is not neutral when it comes to the faith.  The modern left is deliberately attacking foundational truths of God's order, including but not limited to:
- God's creating us male and female
- The importance of the family
- The very notion of objective truth
- The nature of atonement and sins</p>

<p>![](/assets/img/CleanShot 2022-08-29 at 10.04.22.png)</p>

<p>The modern left isn't neutral - they are on the attack.  Anytime a Christian tries to vote his values we are "Christian nationalists."  People who are pro-life and pro-order are "facists."  Make no mistake about it - if you believe the Bible to be true and actually want to live it, you are the enemy.</p>

<h2>2. The left holds all of the power to indoctrinate our children.</h2>

<p>The public school system is just about wholly taken over by leftist ideologues.  I live in an extremely red town in Illinois.  Even in our small town high school we have lectures on pronouns, teachers and staff encouraging transgenderism, and even students who "identify as feline."<br />
![](/assets/img/CleanShot 2022-08-29 at 10.12.25.png)
If public schools are bad, secular universities are far worse.  Reading the student newspaper from our local university (Eastern Illinois University) feels like going into the twilight zone.  Every leftist talking point is assumed true.  Students regularly engage in ridiculous protests for far-left issues.  A student who attends our church and is studying history there told me that the 1619 Project was introduced and discussed <em>in week one of freshman year.</em></p>

<h2>3. Young men (in particular) are lost and angry.</h2>

<p>The fallout of this leftism has hurt young men the most.  White males (especially Christian white males) are the villain in every story.  Toxic masculinity and patriarchy are the named evils being fought against in classrooms across the country.</p>

<p>In response to this, many young men are either giving in and embracing the ideology, checking out and consuming themselves with video games and porn, or turning to angry corners of the internet and radical forms of politics.</p>

<h2>4. The left and right are not moral equals.</h2>

<p>The American right has its problems.  Donald Trump is basically the living embodiment of everything Proverbs warned us about - and Donald Trump is absolutely <strong>worshipped</strong> by large swaths of the American right.  The right is often petty, short-sighted, mean-spirited and has a bad habit of committing unforced errors.</p>

<p>But <strong>for all the right's sins, the right and left in our country are NOT moral equals.</strong>  One side may be hypocritically co-opting biblical Christianity, but the other is outright attacking it.  One side might glorify a man who exemplifies toxic masculinity - the other side attacks the very idea of gender and godly order.</p>

<p>If you think it is all a reaction against Trump, you have a very short memory.  They attacked Mitt Romney (Mitt Milquetoast Romney!) as a racist, sexist homophobe.  They made fun of his family and his wife.  They tried a similar treatment with John McCain (John "Is he even a republican" McCain!).  This isn't about Trump - it's an attack on God's created order and anybody who dares to represent it.</p>

<p>The left has been on war footing for at least the last twenty years, and what they have been warring against isn't toxic republican politics - it's anything that reminds them of traditional morality.  We are now living in a day when the federal government is openly advocating giving hysterectomies and mastectomies to 15 year olds, when small town public schools are putting litter boxes in their gender-neutral bathrooms, and where drag shows are being put on for small children in public libraries - and none of that is coming from the right.</p>

<h2>5. People need to see the Biblical vision</h2>

<p>If the church can't show a biblical alternative to the madness - who will?  If a church can't stand against this blatant anti-God foolishness - who will?  If the church can't show young men why they were made and young women why they were made - who will?</p>

<p>There are plenty of radical voices on the internet speaking to those lost in the madness - but they aren't grounded in the truth and grace of the gospel.</p>

<p>We desperately need to recover a vision of the beauty of God's creation and the beauty of His truth.  We especially need to speak up where the powers of darkness are fighting the strongest.  We need to be completely unambiguous about this and we need to do it in love.</p>

<p>That is why I'm not shying away from the political culture war anymore.  I wish we weren't living in this time - but we are.  If we don't speak up for the truth, who will?</p>

<h2>Closing clarifications:</h2>

<p>I'm not recommending you make your pulpit a wing of the republican party.  I'm merely saying I've made the deliberate decision to stop shying away from cultural issues that have become political and I want to be unambiguous where I stand.</p>

<p>I'm probably as disgusted as you are at preachers bringing in political candidates and endorsing people for office.  I'm not going to give my pulpit time over to Ron Desantis or Donald Trump - it's for talking about Jesus.</p>

<p>But I am going to be loud and clear about things like:
- Biblical marriage
- God making us male and female
- The goodness of both masculinity and femininity
- The evil of abortion
- The nature of forgiveness from sin and abiding guilt (and how CRT distorts that)
- The traps of indoctrination in the public school system.</p>

<p>I'm not going to shoe-horn these things into an exposition of Romans 3, but when it does come up (and these things come up often in scripture) I'm not going to be afraid to say where we should stand.</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/against-missionary-videos</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/against-missionary-videos" />
    <title>Against Missionary Videos</title>
    <published>2022-08-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2022-08-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Ryan Hayden</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">I despise missionary videos and think missionaries should go back to simple photo slides.  Before I go further let me deal with some objections:

First, I understand why missionary videos are popular:
- They are easy to share (you can upload to youtube......</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p><img src="/assets/img/avel-chuklanov-6ePuSf5Wago-unsplash-2.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>I despise missionary videos and think missionaries should go back to simple photo slides.  Before I go further let me deal with some objections:</p>

<p>First, I understand <strong>why</strong> missionary videos are popular:
- They are easy to share (you can upload to youtube and attach on emails).
- They are always the same length.
- They <em>CAN</em> be compelling and professional.
- They <em>CAN</em> make a missionary seem like he really has his act together.</p>

<p>Second, I'm the furthest thing from a luddite:
- I cofounded a software company.
- I work every day with the main designers behind prochurch.com and striving together.
- There are six macs in my house.
- I'm typing this on an iPad Pro with a keyboard case.
- My little church has a three camera streaming setup.</p>

<p>So, why do I despise missionary videos?  Let me give you three reasons:</p>

<h2>1.  Missionary videos are hard.</h2>

<p>Missionary videos are an unnecessary difficulty in the deputation process.</p>

<h3>A. They are hard for the missionary.</h3>

<p>I know what it takes to produce a good video.  I've been working on acquiring that skill for years.  I have a whole closet full of video equipment and hundreds of hours of practice in Final Cut.  I <em>still</em> don't feel like I'm any good at making videos.</p>

<p>Some missionaries luck out and have a great videographer friend or family member who makes a video for them.  Other missionaries spend a king's ransom to have a video made by a decent videographer.  Most missionaries, however, don't even know how to get started, and thus most of the videos are, well, <strong>not great.</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>The music is overpowering.</li>
<li>The audio isn't mixed right.</li>
<li>The transitions are distracting.</li>
<li>etc.</li>
</ul>

<p>So in most cases, the videos don't make you look more professional.  In most cases, the videos expose you as someone who thinks they are professional and doesn't realize how far they have to go.</p>

<h3>B. They are hard to play in church.</h3>

<p>My church has a nice sound system, two flatscreens on the wall and a bunch of macs.  We pay for and use really good presentation software - we still manage to mess up missionary videos nearly every time.  For some reason, the audio very rarely works as we would expect it to, and more often than not, it leads to this awkward hustle as we try to make the video work.</p>

<p>Now, if my church struggles with this, I can only imagine how the many churches with less technical talent are doing with it.</p>

<h2>2. Missionary slides are great.</h2>

<p>I actually miss the old days when they would dim the lights in the room and the missionary would haul out a giant slide projector with a rotary hopper full of actual slides and talk through them one by one.  I'm not saying we should go back to that - but the modern equivalent would just be a powerpoint file with some photos in it, that a missionary just talks through.</p>

<p>And please - missionaries - don't get fancy with the file.  Don't use it to show off your graphic design prowess.  Don't use fancy templates and PLEASE don't use transitions.  Just show us photos of your mission field and talk about the photos.  No technical skills required.  Give us the digital version of the old school slide projector.</p>

<h2>3. Missionaries shouldn't care about looking "professional."</h2>

<p>Missionaries - if you are reading this:  You aren't professionals.  You aren't graphic designers.  You aren't selling software.  You are missionaries.  Just be missionaries.</p>

<p>Some of the best and most effective missionaries I know barely know how to use a computer.  Some of the ones who are killing it in the field almost never even send a prayer letter and when they do, it looks like it was made on a typewriter.  When they do, often they commit graphic design faux pas like using Papyrus for everything.</p>

<p>I don't care.  Not even in the slightest.  We aren't supporting a traveling graphic designer, we are supporting a missionary.</p>

<ul>
<li>Are you preaching the gospel?</li>
<li>Are you training nationals?</li>
<li>Are you starting churches?</li>
</ul>

<p>That's all that should matter.</p>

<p>Now, I understand that some churches have unrealistic expectations on this matter: shame on them.  I understand that some churches judge your future effectiveness as a missionary in Zambia by the weight and layout of your prayer cards (as if your skills in InDesign make a meaningful difference in God's ability to use you on the field).  I say "a curse on the whole thing."  <strong>Let missionaries be missionaries - not marketers.</strong></p>

<p>Also, I acknowledge that materials and slides are a necessary evil.  Whether we like it or not, if your prayer card looks dated or ugly - it does say something about your family.  I recognize all of this - but the video trend should have been seen as a sign we've taken that expectation too far.</p>

<p>It bothers me to think that some young couple out there right now is trying to get to the mission field, and they are going to spend five thousand dollars for a videographer to make a compelling and professional video.  It bothers me more that missionaries on the field feel like they need to spend their hard earned time or scant resources producing a video.   It bothers me most that this has become the expectation of many churches.</p>

<p>Let's make this missionary video thing go the way of the dinosaur.</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/2012-02-09-why-fundamentalism-biblical-separation</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/2012-02-09-why-fundamentalism-biblical-separation" />
    <title>Why Fundamentalism: Biblical Separation</title>
    <published>2012-02-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-02-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Ryan Hayden</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">Over the last few weeks, I have written a few articles critical of the fundamentalist movement. One might wonder (and some have through comments, phone calls, and emails) why I still consider myself a fundamentalist when the movement has such obvious......</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>Over the last few weeks, I have written a few articles critical of the fundamentalist movement. One might wonder (and some have through comments, phone calls, and emails) why I still consider myself a fundamentalist when the movement has such obvious problems.</p>

<p>The main reason (and there are others) why I will always be a fundamentalist and why I do not consider myself an evangelical or even a conservative evangelical is because I believe in the biblical doctrine of Ecclesiastical separation. What is this doctrine of Ecclesiastical separation? I'm glad you asked.</p>

<h2>First some history</h2>

<p>In the later part of the 1800s, the world was in the beginning stages of a radical technological revolution. It seemed like overnight people were figuring out problems that had plagued the world for ages: like how to cut down on death rates in surgery (Joseph Lister), how to keep your house lit at night without burning something (Thomas Edison), and how to efficiently move stuff and people from point A to point B (Trains and automobiles). By the early 1900s, scientific advancement had produced so many lifestyle improvements that it seemed like the world had been changed for the better overnight. People placed a great deal of hope in science and the scientific method, and openly predicted a time when the world's evils would be made a thing of the past by scientific and technological betterment. They didn't know that the scientific ideas they uplifted would produce the gassings and killings of World War 1, the Eugenics movement, and ultimately the Haulocost. Science was the messiah of the day, and questioning science was sacrilege.</p>

<p>Because of this, many religious leaders started to take a second look at scripture and question the things that were "non-scientific". The creation, the crossing of the Red Sea, the virgin birth of Christ, the inspiration of scripture and many more scriptural teachings came under the scrutiny of these self styled "Modernists" or "Progressives". Organizations that had long stood firm for the principles of scripture (Like the Presbyterian Church USA, the American Baptist and Southern Baptist Conventions in the USA and the Baptist Union in England) began to be infiltrated and influenced by these "Theological Liberals". In a short time they had secured places of leadership in denominational colleges and seminaries.</p>

<p>These changes did not go unnoticed by faithful pastors and teachers and many of them stood up for the "faith once delivered to the saints". People like J. Gresham Machen of Princeton Seminary and Charles Spurgeon in London went on the attack for the "fundamentals of the faith" and tried to rid their respective denominations of doctrinal deviants. When these and others were unsuccessful, they left, either starting their own denominations (like the General Association of Regular Baptist Churches and the Orthodox Presbyterian Church) or choosing to remain independent of any denomination. These pioneer fundamentalists paid a heavy price, often losing their retirement funds, having their ordinations revoked and being formally blackballed by their old associations.</p>

<p>The principle these men (and later generations of fundamentalists) invoked in their exodus of mainline denominations was ecclesiastical separation.</p>

<h2>Ecclesiastical Separation:</h2>

<p>Ecclesiastical separation is the refusal to associate with churches, leaders, or institutions that reject the open teaching of scripture.</p>

<p>Not many pastors and churches practice ecclesiastical separation - most of those who do are considered "fundamentalists" and are thus marginalized by mainstream christianity - so you would think that scripture says little about this subject. After all, if so many pastors and leaders aren't practicing ecclesiastical separation, surely there isn't any clear cut scriptural doctrine on it.</p>

<p>One would think that, but one would be wrong.</p>

<p>There are many passages that, if followed, would result in clear convictions about ecclesiastical separation. Consider 1 Timothy 6:3-5:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>"If any man teach otherwise, and consent not to wholesome words, even the words of our Lord Jesus Christ, and to the doctrine which is according to godliness; He is proud, knowing nothing, but doting about questions and strifes of words, whereof cometh envy, strife, railings, evil surmisings, Perverse disputings of men of corrupt minds, and destitute of the truth, supposing that gain is godliness: from such withdraw thyself."</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Notice Paul's succinct advise to Timothy on dealing with false teachers: <strong><em>"from such withdraw thyself"</em></strong>. Sounds like separation to me.</p>

<p>Consider also Romans 16:17</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>"Now I beseech you, brethren, mark them which cause divisions and offenses contrary to the doctrine which ye have learned; and avoid them."</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Again, what possible interpretation of that verse could be made other than that we are to mark and separate from those who teach false doctrine. Mark them, avoid them. Pretty clear.</p>

<p>We could go on. A quick perusal of 2 John or the book of Jude would make you think ecclesiastical separation should be a foregone conclusion to any open minded student of scripture. Unfortunately, it's not.</p>

<p>There are many evangelicals who, though they themselves believe in the clear teachings of the Bible, are more than willing to associate with those who do not. They, through their denominations, endorsements, speaking engagements and other allegiances profess to stand for the truth while standing next to those who are tearing it apart.</p>

<p>I'm sorry, but that's not for me.</p>

<p>A relationship with Christ demands purity. Just as my relationship with my wife keeps me from close association with women my age, my relationship to Christ and to His word keeps me out of association with those who are tearing down His teaching and denying His self-professed character.</p>

<p>That is why I am a fundamentalist: Ecclesiastical Separation.</p>

<h2>Errant Ideas About Separation:</h2>

<p>Unfortunately, I can't stop there. Many people label themselves a fundamentalist and profess to believe in separation but distort it. They take this Biblical doctrine, meant to keep the body of Christ pure, and they use it to preserve their own clique or to insulate themselves from any criticism.</p>

<p>There is a big difference between ecclesiastical separation based on principle and flowing out of obedience to Christ and God's word and ecclesiastical separation as a convenient excuse to never explain your positions, to exercise control over your tribe, and to prevent any changes from occurring in your church or movement.</p>

<p>I want to point out three errant variants of ecclesiastical separation, which are, unfortunately pretty prevalent in modern fundamentalist "circles":</p>

<h3>Camp Separation</h3>

<p>Camp Separation is refusing fellowship with other churches because they aren't a part of your particular tribe. I've heard of churches who will only fellowship with churches and pastors who graduated from Hyles Anderson College. I've heard of churches who refuse to take on missionaries because they are supported by independent Bible churches, and I've heard of baptist churches breaking fellowship with a man because he preached for a fundamentalist group of Presbyterians.</p>

<p>In each of those cases, it was obvious that ecclesiastical separation was invoked not because of doctrinal error, but because of harmless labels and associations.</p>

<p>I'm afraid that in the arms of the wrong men, ecclesiastical separation is little more than a weapon to use against Christian brothers who dare to think for themselves. The doctrine of separation was never meant to be a whip to scare young preachers into staying in a certain circle, but unfortunately I think that is how it is often used.</p>

<h4>Everythingism Separation</h4>

<p>Closely tied to camp separation is what I would call everythingism separation. Whereas fundamentalist refuse to associate with those who don't agree with them on the fundamentals of the faith, everythingist refuse to associate with those who don't agree with them on everything.</p>

<p>I've heard of pastors who were ridiculed and pushed out of fellowship for growing goatees, for using a screen in church, or for having midweek services at a different time than on wednesday night at 7:00 p.m..</p>

<p>No where is this kind of separation more evident in fundamentalism than in the area of music. I've heard many many times that a church was "off" in their music and needed to be avoided. The churches in question weren't bringing electric guitars into their service, they weren't hiring a "praise team" or rapping out for Jesus. Usually, they were just using a style of music that was unfamiliar or different from what their critics used. For example, I have many times heard West Coast Baptist College criticized for their music and they recently produced <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Music-Matters-Understanding-Applying-Amazing/dp/1598940376/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1328821629&amp;sr=8-1">a book</a> which is, in my opinion, the best polemic in support of conservative Christian music I have ever read.</p>

<p>Again, this kind of ecclesiastical separation ends up just being a tool that pastors and leaders use to control and threaten their followers.</p>

<h4>Old Paths Separation</h4>

<p>The last errant variety of separation that I see in fundamentalism today is "Old Paths" Separation. There are pastors who are threatened by anything new, even if it is outside of the realm of biblical criticism, and they want to form fellowships that insulate them from any change.</p>

<p>Culture changes and culture has changed. The Bible is mute in some areas where culture has changed. The Bible says nothing, for instance about what type of microphone you use or whether or not you use a screen in church. The Bible says nothing about your use of facebook, twitter or the church website (although it says a lot about how we communicate, and those rules still apply). The Bible says nothing specific about pews, architectural styles, or even about dressing up in church. (Did it ever occur to people that most of the Christians in the world probably don't have two changes of clothes, never mind a suit?) There are biblical principles that apply to all of those areas, but those biblical principles don't necessarily cement churches into being exactly what they were in 1960.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, some pastors will use ecclesiastical separation (or the threat of ecclesiastical separation) to try to insulate their church from change. The pastor is free to determine the direction of their church, but using the doctrine of separation to manipulate people is wrong, plain and simple.</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/2012-02-07-how-fundamentalism-sets-up-young-men-for-disillusionment</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/2012-02-07-how-fundamentalism-sets-up-young-men-for-disillusionment" />
    <title>How Fundamentalism Sets Up Young Men for Disillusionment</title>
    <published>2012-02-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2012-02-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Ryan Hayden</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">disillusion: disappointment resulting from the discovery that something is not as good as one believed it to be:


I love fundamentalism and consider myself a fundamentalist. The principles of fundamentalism are where the attraction is for me. Which is......</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <blockquote>
  <p>disillusion: disappointment resulting from the discovery that something is not as good as one believed it to be:</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I love fundamentalism and consider myself a fundamentalist. The principles of fundamentalism are where the attraction is for me. Which is why I'll always be a fundamentalist. Anybody with eyes right now, however, can see than many people my age are leaving fundamentalism and getting bitter.</p>

<p>What has struck me as odd is the character of these defectors. The ones I have known were not in my opinion natural rebels. Some of the most thoughtful, submissive, and serious students at my fundamentalist alma mater have since "abandoned ship."</p>

<p>I want to suggest that the reason we are losing so many of our "best and brightest" is because in many areas of fundamentalism, we are setting people up for disillusionment.</p>

<p>The truth is that there is no perfect institution. There is no perfect church, there is no perfect publishing house, there is no perfect pastor, there is no perfect college. Sooner or later, flaws will surface and need to be dealt with.</p>

<p>This is where the rub lies in the case of fundamentalism. Fundamentalist institutions, in my opinion, have a very poor track record when it comes to dealing with their flaws. More often then not, when flaws come to the surface, they are denied, then justified, then defended, and finally codified into the fabric of the institution.</p>

<p>Try, for example, to convince a graduate of Hyles Anderson that there is a flaw in their college, any flaw, and more often then not you'll get railed on. The same could be said of devoted readers of the <em>Sword of the Lord</em> or followers of many other fundamentalist institutions. In the eyes of many, fundamentalist institutions have achieved something most organizations covet, they are above criticism.</p>

<p>To be above criticism is to be perfect. When people think that something is perfect, and find out otherwise, they often get disillusioned.</p>

<p>I think this disillusionment is so prevalent among young fundamentalists for several reasons:</p>

<h3>Reason 1: Leader worship is encouraged.</h3>

<p>Last week, the news kept playing a clip of the Atlanta Heretic, "Bishop" Eddie Long, being coronated in front of his church, wrapped in a ridiculous crimson cloth and what looked like a biblical scroll. The preacher narrating this ceremony kept saying "We elevate you from a commoner to the kingship."</p>

<p>While this ceremony was outside of fundamentalism. Many fundamentalist pastors might as well stage their own ridiculous ceremony, because in the eyes of many, they have been elevated from "a commoner to the kingship." I see no reason why pastors should not receive honor, after all the Bible does say <em>"Let the elders that rule well be counted worthy of double honour, especially they who labour in the word and doctrine."</em> At some point however, honor turns into insulation from all criticism, and when you teach ideas for a living, insulation isn't healthy.</p>

<p>Because fundamentalist leaders are put on so high a pedestal and thought so highly of, criticism of them, any criticism of them, becomes taboo. Some fundamentalist pastors are so revered that people rush to their defense, often thoughtlessly, whenever they are criticized.</p>

<p>In my experience, people revere these leaders because they are worthy of it. When a man is instrumental in leading you to Christ, or opens up the scripture for you in a way no one has before, that person becomes special to you. When God has His hand on a church and you learn wonderful things there, it becomes a milestone for you. When things are special to you it is only natural for you to want to protect them.</p>

<p>You can become so protective of someone that they cease to be human. They become essentially infallible. Again, things above criticism have to be perfect.</p>

<h3>Reason 2: Fundamentalism becomes everything-ism.</h3>

<p>Precisely because leaders are above criticism, over time, those who follow them cease to be fundamentalists - fellowshipping only around the fundamentals and become everythingists - insisting that you prescribe to every idea of their chosen leader.</p>

<p>Everythingism would work if leaders were perfect. It's ok to be an everythingist about Jesus' ideas. The ideas of men - not so much.</p>

<p>The fundamentals used to be a set of biblical truths. You separated from people who denied the fundamentals. The fundamentals have become whatever your leader decides they are. Unfortunately, people today will deny fellowship with you over such insignificant issues as men's hair styles, women's fashions, the slightest variation in music styles, whether the pastor decides to use a screen in church, or even the type of microphone he uses.</p>

<p>Because the leaders are over-revered, the leaders opinions become the orthodoxy of their followers and this orthodoxy is unchallenged in that particular camp. Again, this sets up young people for disillusionment, because as soon as they are exposed to any other orthodoxy, the one they were around previously comes in question, and when something which was previously above criticism has to be weighed next to alternatives, disillusionment is inevitable.</p>

<h3>Reason 3: Non-fundamentalist religious leaders are unfairly criticized.</h3>

<p>Another cause for disillusionment among young fundamentalist is the unfair treatment of non-fundamentalist leaders, or even fundamentalist leaders from a "different camp." This, in my opinion, is really just a natural result of leader worship and everythingism and it is usually where disillusionment comes to the surface.</p>

<p>If a leader is above criticism, and his ideas and opinions become the orthodoxy of his followers, any leader whose opinions or ideas challenge his own becomes a threat. The truth is there are many people who are not fundamentalists or outside of the fundamentalist camp who are sincere Bible preachers, are very talented and are fighting for the fundamentals of the faith. These men may be radio preachers (like John MacArthur or Ravi Zacharias), authors (like David Platt) or evangelists (like Paul Washer). These men don't agree with fundamentalists on everything (that's why they don't call themselves fundamentalists) but that doesn't make them heretics of the first order or even a threat to be blackballed.</p>

<p>Its common for fundamentalists to just label people "a liberal" or "a neo-evangelical" or "off" and just move on. The impression this leaves in the mind of young fundamentalists is that these men are tools in the hands of satan. When, as is bound to happen eventually, a young man discovers that these men have something valuable to say, and are far closer to fundamentalism than they ever imagined, disillusionment happens.</p>

<h2>Conclusion:</h2>

<p>So how do we fix this? Is there a way to keep young fundamentalists young fundamentalists? Is there a way to cut down on defections and keep disillusionment at bay? I think a few simple changes would do away with a lot of it.</p>

<p><strong>First, fundamentalist leaders need to insist that they are human and discourage the kind of insulation from any criticism that comes from over-reverence.</strong> I'm not saying they should encourage people to be critical - that would be catastrophic. What I am saying is that they need to encourage people to weigh their ideas next to scripture. They need to aim for their church to be as the Bereans where, who didn't just accept Paul's teaching at face value, but searched the scriptures first.</p>

<p><strong>Second, fundamentalist leaders need to find a way to allow for some disagreement.</strong> If they continue to force people to swallow the whole pill, disillusionment is going to be one of the side effects. I'm glad I went to a fundamentalist bible college that encouraged people to be thinkers and didn't kick people out just for questioning the ideas of the founder, but I've heard many stories of places where this isn't the case. As long as fundamentalist circles have an idea-gestapo people are going to be fleeing to the free world, whether it is to their hurt or not.</p>

<p><strong>Third, fundamentalists leaders need to approach people outside of our circles fairly.</strong> We do not need to impugn their motives, label them, or condemn their ministry. Instead, we could take any differences we have with them and use them as a springboard to discuss ideas. How refreshing would it be to hear someone say "John MacArthur is a good Bible teacher with a lot to teach, but I disagree with him about Bible versions, church polity, and I think he's a little high handed with his calvinism. Also, he preached in some places that seem inconsistent with his message of standing up for biblical truth. If you want to discuss it more, I'd love to talk about it in private." This would go a lot further with young people than "he's a heritic" or "he's a liberal", which, unfortunately is what we often get.</p>

<p>I think that if leaders commit to these things, many of our "best and brightest" would stop jumping fences, and would instead use their considerable talents and collective intellect to build the kind fundamentalist churches and institutions that we dearly need.</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/2011-08-29-five-steps-to-writing-a-sermon-my-sermon-writing-system</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/2011-08-29-five-steps-to-writing-a-sermon-my-sermon-writing-system" />
    <title>5 Steps to Writing a Sermon</title>
    <published>2011-08-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2011-08-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Ryan Hayden</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">Recently, someone asked me how I prepare sermons. I dont know why anybody would be interested in this information, but I do think I have found a system that works (for me).




One of the things that has helped me immensely is to plan out my sermons......</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>Recently, someone asked me how I prepare sermons. I dont know why anybody would be interested in this information, but I do think I have found a system that works (for me).</p>

<ol>
<li><h3>Plan out expository sermon series well in advance.</h3>

<p>One of the things that has helped me immensely is to plan out my sermons by series well in advance of when I preach. The main reason I do this is because it gives me a plan of study that keeps me from wondering off into tangent sermons. I have found this idea of planning to be super useful not just for preaching but for teaching as well, I plan out every lecture for the whole year when I have to teach a course and it takes something big and makes it small enough to handle.</p>

<p>Some would say that this level of planning hinders the work of the Holy Spirit, but I would say the opposite is true. I have found that the planned sermons are just what I need and just what the congregation needs. No one can complain that I am picking on them if I preach on something going on now, because I planned out the sermon six months ago.</p></li>
<li><h3>Read, re-read, and re-reread the passage. Write down any ideas that come to mind as Evernote notes.</h3>

<p>About a week before I need to preach a sermon, I start to read and reread the passage of scripture that I am preaching on. I do this during a separate time from my personal devotions. Usually, after I have read a passage through several times, some idea of how to best present the theme or truth in the passage comes to mind and I write in down in Evernote.</p>

<p>I almost never use the first outline that comes to mind, it usually takes me several revisions. I can access both my notes on the passage and the passage itself via my iPad pretty much wherever I am at.</p></li>
<li><h3>Read (or listen to) relevant material on the subject from other men.</h3>

<p>After I have read a passage through a sufficient number of times to get the feel for the passage myself, I will read some commentaries and listen to others preach on the passage. I love sermonaudio.com for this, as I can look up sermons by passage. Sometimes, I will listen to sermons or read commentaries that I wouldnt recommend to just anybody.</p>

<p>All the while as I am doing this I will continue to put notes into Evernote. After a few days I will have quite a large number of little text files containing outline idea, quotes and relevant cultural and historical information.</p></li>
<li><h3>Write out a full sermon manuscript.</h3>

<p>My next step is to write out a sermon manuscript. I am not a manuscript preacher, but I do not feel prepared unless I have a full manuscript written out. I rarely say all that I have written, and almost always veer off of my manuscript while preaching, but I still think this stage is invaluable. Joseph Parker said that if you dont know what you are going to say before you preach, you probably wont know what you said when you are finished (and your congregation wont either.)</p>

<p>While manuscript writing is hard work, it doesnt take nearly as much time as reading and ideating about the text. When I have done steps two and three correctly, usally the manuscript just comes together.</p>

<p>(I am very careful to write a manuscript as a speaker and not as a writer. I avoid long sentences and big words, because as I am speaking people cant reread a sentence or examine the context of a word. I try to close my eyes and type as I would speak, that may be the most valuable part of this step.)</p></li>
<li><h3>Winnow down my manuscript to the essentials and print it out to preach.</h3>

<p>I dont like to use a manuscript as I speak. I find that having something to read will make me a reader and not a preacher (the manuscript for me is a crutch, and I cant have it in front of me.) So a day or so after the manuscript has been written, I will read it, make any changes that need to be made and type out an outline that contains:</p>

<ul>
<li>Scripture references that need to be read</li>
<li>Quotes I dont want to mess up</li>
<li>Sentences I dont want to omit</li>
<li>The outline</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>

<p>When this if finished I print it off , fold it in my Bible (which I only use for preaching) and open it again when I am ready to preach.</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/2011-08-11-five-books-on-preaching-and-ministry-im-thankful-for</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://pastorryanhayden.com/blog/2011-08-11-five-books-on-preaching-and-ministry-im-thankful-for" />
    <title>Five Books on Preaching I&#039;m Thankful For</title>
    <published>2011-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2011-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Ryan Hayden</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">Usually, when something is a classic, there is a good reason for it. This book is no different. I got my first copy of this book when I was a freshman in Bible college and have read through many of its chapters over and over. When I got my iPad, this was......</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <ol>
<li><h3><a href="http://ryan-hayden.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/08/books.jpg">![]({{ site.url }}/pictures/2011/08/books-300x198.jpg "Man Reading Book and Sitting on Bookshelf in Library")</a><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Lectures-My-Students-C-Spurgeon/dp/1598565176/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1313089085&amp;sr=8-1" title="Amazon link">Lectures to My Students, <em>Charles Spurgeon</em></a></h3>

<p>Usually, when something is a classic, there is a good reason for it. This book is no different. I got my first copy of this book when I was a freshman in Bible college and have read through many of its chapters over and over. When I got my iPad, this was one of the first books I looked for.</p>

<p>My favorite chapters in this lengthy book are Attention and The Ministers Fainting Fits.</p>

<p>If you really like this book, a similar one by Spurgeon entitled An All Around Ministry is also worth reading. My favorite essay on preaching is a chapter in this book entitled Light, Fire, Faith, Life, Love.</p></li>
<li><h3><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Order-Church-Manual-Ministries/dp/0965285936/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1313089125&amp;sr=1-1" title="amazon link">Order in the Church, <em>Paul Chapel</em></a></h3>

<p>This is the only contemporary book that made the list. Paul Chapel is the pastor of Lancaster Baptist Church in Lancaster California and the founder and president of West Coast Baptist College. This book is a treasure trove of how to organize the church so that everything is done decently and in order. It is full of practical forms and detailed advice on almost every area of the ministry.</p></li>
<li><h3><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Preaching-Preachers-D-Martyn-Lloyd-Jones/dp/0310278708/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1313089163&amp;sr=1-1" title="amazon link">Preaching and Preachers, <em>D. Martyn Lloyd Jones</em></a></h3>

<p>One book that changed my life was D. Martyn Lloyd Jones book Studies in the Sermon on the Mount. Lloyd Jones was pastor of Westminster Chapel in London for the better part of the twentieth century and at one point was one of the most respected preachers in the world. His style isnt for everyone (He was a medical doctor before becoming a preacher and brought a doctors precision to everything he did,) but this book is full of practical advice for an expository preacher.</p></li>
<li><h3><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Ad-Clerum-Advices-Young-Preacher/dp/1459026470/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1313089197&amp;sr=1-1" title="amazon link">Ad Clerum, Advices to a Young Preacher, <em>Joseph Parker</em></a></h3>

<p>In the interest of full disclosure, I havent finished reading this one yet, but I am enjoying it. Joseph Parker was the other pastor in London during the ministry of Charles Spurgeon. His sermons are very easy to read, and he is known as one of the greatest preachers who ever lived.</p>

<p>This book is written partly in a satirical style, and pokes fun at preachers who are mechanical or who show off their knowledge and discipline for its own sake. I have greatly enjoyed reading it and cant wait to finish it.</p></li>
<li><h3><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Expository-preaching-plans-methods-Meyer/dp/B004S9CV2E/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1313089242&amp;sr=1-1" title="amazon link">Expository Preaching Plans and Methods, <em>F.B. Meyer</em></a></h3>

<p>F.B. Meyer is one of my favorite authors, period. I have read and reread his biographical books and always found in them a wealth of insight into the lives of the saints. I have read Meyers other essays with great pleasure as well.</p>

<p>In this book, Meyer attempts to teach young preachers why they should preach through the Bible expositorily, and how to best do it. Far from cold or mechanical, the book, like Meyers preaching, has a devotional life to it, and offers a lot of wisdom.</p></li>
</ol>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
    </feed>
